<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gods mercies and Ierusalems miseries A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, the 25. of Iune. 1609. By Lancelot Dawes, Master of Arts and fellow of Queenes Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Dawes, Lancelot, 1580-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A19953</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6388</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109409</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845057</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845057</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9933</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A19953)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9933)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 579:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Gods mercies and Ierusalems miseries A sermon preached at Pauls Crosse, the 25. of Iune. 1609. By Lancelot Dawes, Master of Arts and fellow of Queenes Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Dawes, Lancelot, 1580-1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[144] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by John Windet] for Cle. Knight,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On Jeremiah V, 1.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-I.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9933:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9933:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GODS MERCIES AND IERVSALEMS MISERIES.</p>
            <p>A Sermon Preached at <hi>Pauls Croſſe, the</hi> 25. <hi>of</hi> Iune. 1609.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Lancelot Dawes,</hi> Maſter of Arts <hi>and Fellow of Queenes Colledge in Oxford.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Matth. 23.37.38.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>¶ O Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem, how often would, &amp;c.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed for <hi>Cle. Knight.</hi> 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9933:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9933:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the Right Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God, <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> Lord Biſhoppe of <hi>Carlile.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Reuerend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Sermon was made for the Croſſe, not intended for the Preſſe. I was by authoritie commanded the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, and by importunitie of many haue at length conſented to the latter. It may perchance
<pb facs="tcp:9933:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> heereafter complaine with the <hi>Satyriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Har. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Deferat in vitem vendentem thus, at odores,</l>
               <l>Et piper, et quicquid chartis amicitur ineptis.</l>
            </q>
            <p>But that is no great diſgrace in theſe daies, it ſhal haue Store of company, perhaps ſome to whom it may deſeruedly giue the wall. As for fault finding carpers, I little account of their cenſure, it is well knowne whoſe liuery they weare, it were a ſtrange peece of worke that ſhould haue their approbation. Some haue charged nature af a groſſe ouerſight for placing the oxe his hornes vpon his head, and not vpon his ſhoulders which are the ſtronger, an inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous reader will winke at a
<pb facs="tcp:9933:3"/> fault, and approoue that which is good. But let theſe paſſe, my humble deſire is, that this mite which I haue caſt into the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury (for my riches extend not to a talent) may find acceptance with your good Lordſhip, who may iuſtly claime the ſame inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in me which <hi>Paul</hi> did in <hi>Philemon.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ. <hi>19.</hi> Seneca. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de benefic. Cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Thou oweſt vnto mee euen thine owne ſelfe.</hi> I willingly acknowledge it: and ſay as <hi>Aeſchines</hi> in <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> ſaid to <hi>Socrates: Seeing I haue nothing to offer wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy ſo reuerend a Perſon.</hi> (for to dedicate a Sermon to your Lordſhippe is but with <hi>Chaerilus</hi> to preſent a few
<pb facs="tcp:9933:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> harſh verſes to <hi>Alexander) I offer my ſelfe;</hi> promiſing still to continue.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don <date>the <hi>27.</hi> of Iune.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips in all humble duetie and Seruice.</hi> Lancelot Dawes.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:9933:4"/>
            <head>GODS MERCIES AND IERVSALEMS MISERIES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>IEREMIE 5.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>¶ Runne two and fro by the ſtreetes of Ieruſalem, and behold now, and know and inquire in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen places thereof: if yee can find a man, or if there be any that executeth Judgement and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the trueth and J will ſpare it.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Any meanes did the Lord vſe to reclaim IERVSA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LEM from her rebellion againſt him, by ſundry
<pb facs="tcp:9933:5"/> commemorations of his benefites he wooed her by the ſweet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the Goſpell, he incited her by the captiuity of her ſiſter <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria,</hi> he forwarned her, but yet ſhe continued like her forefathers,<note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal:</hi> 78.</note> 
               <hi>a faithles and ſtubborne generation, a generation that ſet not her heart a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right,</hi> ſhe runnes ſtill on a wrong Bias, in ſtead of beeing a <hi>faithfull Spouſe,</hi> ſhe becomes a filthy harlot, and<note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iere.</hi> 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>playeth the Whore vpon euery hie mountaine, and vnder euery greene tree, her</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.22.</note> 
               <hi>wine is mixed with water, her ſiluer is become droſse, her Princes rebels and companions of theeues,</hi> and as ſhee groweth in yeares, ſo ſhee increaſeth in all impieties, ſhee which at the firſt did onely pull little ſinnes with the ſmall<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jſa.</hi> 5.18.</note> 
               <hi>cordes of vanity,</hi> doth now draw greater tranſgreſſions with the huge <hi>cart-ropes of iniquity,</hi> ſo that now
<pb facs="tcp:9933:5"/>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>from the ſole of her foot to the crown of her head, there is nothing found in her but woundes and ſwellings, and ſores full of corruption.</hi> In this caſe God<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 5.4.</note> which cannot abide wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, neither can any euill dwell with him, (as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſpeaketh) beginnes to loath her, and to giue her vp into the hands of her moſt ſauage and cruell enemies, (the <hi>Chaldeans) who ſhall</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 79.1.</note> 
               <hi>defile the holy Temple, and make Ieruſalem a heape of ſtones.</hi> Oh, but ſhall the husband be ſo vnkind to his Spouſe<note n="k" place="margin">Ier. 2.2</note> 
               <hi>whome hee hath married vnto himſelfe?</hi> ſhall a Father be ſo ſeuere to his child? ſhall the God of mercy bee ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merciful vnto his choſen?<note n="l" place="margin">Gen. 18.25</note> 
               <hi>Shall not the iudge of the world doe right? farre be it from God, that hee ſhould ſlay the righteous with the wicked.</hi> God an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth, that there is no reaſon, why ſhee ſhould repine againſt
<pb facs="tcp:9933:6"/> him, or accuſe him of cruelty: her Apoſtaſie is ſo generall, her diſeaſe (like a <hi>Gangraena</hi>) is ſpread through euery member of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, her malice is ſo incurable, that hee cannot without impeachment of his iuſtice, ſpare her any longer. <hi>Runne to and fro by the ſtreetes of Ieruſalem, &amp;c.</hi> v. 8. O yee men of Iuda and inhabitants of Ieruſalem, doe not ſay that your teeth are ſet on edge, becauſe<note n="m" place="margin">Ezech. 18</note> 
               <hi>your fathers haue eaten ſowre grapes,</hi> doe not obiect, that <hi>my wayes are not equall, it is your wayes that are vnequall:</hi> it is your ſinnes that bringes this heauy doome vpon your heads: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be ſo or not, you your ſelues bee Iudges: for I beſeech you ſeeke vppe and downe, not in the Country townes onely, and villages of Iudah, but in the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolis of the whole Kingdome,
<pb facs="tcp:9933:6"/> in the<note n="n" place="margin">Math. 4. Iſa. 52.1.</note> 
               <hi>holie Citie,</hi> runne through euery corner of it, ſearch and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire in the houſes and allyes and backe-lanes, and high ſtreetes ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, marke their conditions, obſerue their practiſes, conſider their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour, take a full view of their whole carriage, if after ſuch enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, there bee found but one man amongſt the whole multitude that feareth me, or maketh any conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his wayes, and I will ſpare the whole City for that one mans ſake: but if after you haue ſought man by man, there bee not one godly man found amongſt them all, thinke it not cruelty, if now at length I inflict (in iuſtice) my iudgments vpon her: the ſumme is contained in this ſhort propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: <hi>I will ſpare Ieruſalem, if there can one righteous man bee found in her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein we may obſerue theſe
<pb facs="tcp:9933:7"/> two principall pointes: Gods mercy, in that hee would haue ſpared <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> for one mans ſake; <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> miſery, in that not one righteous man can bee found in her; the former I deliuer in this propoſition; <hi>Gods mercie in ſparing doth exceede his iuſtice in puniſhing,</hi> and with this wee will beginne.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> But alas, who am I duſt and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes that I ſhould intreate of this Subiect? it is a bottomleſſe depth, who can diue into it? it is an vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>acceſſible light, who can beholde it?<note place="margin">Tull de. natu. deorum.</note> if the Heathen <hi>Simonides</hi> after three dayes ſtudy how to deſcribe God, was further from any reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution in the latter end, then when hee firſt beganne: nay, if<note n="o" place="margin">Exod. 33.</note> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> (a man more familiar with God then any that euer liued vpon the face of the earth) when he was put in a clift of a rocke, and couered
<pb facs="tcp:9933:7"/> with Gods hands, could not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the glory of his face; then may it not ſeeme ſtrange, if the tongues of men and Angels faile in deſcribing the very backe parts of this one attribute, being more proper and eſſentiall vnto God then any whatſoeuer.<note place="margin">Iuſtin lib. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> That <hi>Tyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> proued the wiſeſt in the end, who hauing concluded in the Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning with his fellowes, that hee which could firſt in the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning behold the Sun (which they worſhipped as a God) ſhould bee King; looked not toward the Eaſt where hee riſeth, but towards the weſterne mountaines where his rayes did firſt appeare. We will follow his Example and ſeeing we cannot ſeeke into the fountaine at which the <hi>Cherubs</hi> did couer their faces: let vs behold it in the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, that is, the Prophetes and
<pb facs="tcp:9933:8"/> Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Hierom. lib. <hi>110.</hi> Comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in Ezech.</note> as <hi>Ierome</hi> expounds the word, or the mountaines, that is the creatures and works of God, in all which it doth moſt clearely ſhine: there is no worke of God in al which there doth not appeare ſuch manifeſt Characters of his mercy, that he which runneth may reade them. Thoſe benefites in tended towards his children, as namely Election before all time, creation in the beginning of time, Vocation, Redemption, Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the fulnes of time, Glorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation after all time, &amp;c. To proue them to bee ſo many riuers of the bottomles Ocean of Gods neuer dying mercy; it were but to buſie my ſelfe about a principle, which I hope none of you will call into queſtion: Gods almighty power is manifeſted vnto vs, in that hee hath created the world of nothing,
<pb facs="tcp:9933:8"/>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 33.6.</note> 
               <hi>and made all the hoaſt of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by the breath of his mouth,</hi> and it is a property in deſcribing of which Gods Secretaries do ſtriue to be eloquent, <hi>Iob</hi> to ſhew it ſaith that<note n="q" place="margin">Iob. 9.</note> 
               <hi>he ſpreadeth out the heauens like a Canopie, and walketh vpon the the height of the Sea, that he maketh the ſtarres</hi> Arcturus <hi>and</hi> Orion, <hi>and</hi> Pleiades, <hi>and the climates of the South. Elihu</hi> ſets it forth vnder <hi>Benoth, whoſe taile is like a Cedar,</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Iob. 40.</note> 
               <hi>and his bones like ſtaues of braſſe, yet the Lord leadeth him whither ſoeuer hee will;</hi> and vnder <hi>Leuiathan, which makes the depth to boile like a pot, and the ſea like a pot of oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and yet the Lord can put a hooke in his noſe, and pearce his iawes with an Angle. Dauid</hi> to ſhew it, ſayth that hee maketh the <hi>mountaines to skippe like Rammes, and the little hils like young ſheepe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 114.</note> I ſay, to expreſſe it
<pb facs="tcp:9933:9"/> ſayth, <hi>that</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Iſa. 40.</note> 
               <hi>all nations before him are as a droppe of a bucket, and are counted as the duſt of the ballance, that he taketh away the Iſles as a little duſt, that hee hath meaſured the waters in his fiſt, &amp; counted heauen with a ſpan, &amp; comprehended the duſt of the earth in a meaſure, and weighed the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines in a weight, and the hilles in a ballance,</hi> and yet his mercy goeth beyond his power, in that his om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotency hath made nothing but what his mercy moued him to cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, and it comes after too, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing, and guiding, and prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting, by his heauenly prouidence (a branch of his mercy) whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer his powerfull hand hath made, if hee ſhould but once ſtoppe the influence of his mercy, al the works of his hands ſhould preſently bee annihilated.<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 33.5.</note> The earth is full of the mercies of the Lord (ſayth the
<pb facs="tcp:9933:9"/> 
               <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi>) hee ſayth not the heauens ſayth <hi>Auſten, Quia non indigent miſericordia vbi eſt nulla miſeria:</hi> they needed no mercy where there is no miſerie;<note place="margin">Auguſtin in illum locum.</note> and yet in another place hee addeth the heauens to <hi>thy truth</hi> (an other of his attributes) goeth <hi>vnto the clouds,</hi> there it ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, but thy mercy goeth further:<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.5.9</note> 
               <hi>it reacheth vnto the heauens,</hi> in few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er wordes: <hi>It is ouer all his works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But my text leades me to entreat of his mercy, as it hath reference vnto his iuſtice; where you ſhall find that of two infinites one doth infinitely ſurpaſſe an other, to bee called a mercifull God, and the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of mercy is a title wherein God eſpecially delighteth, but he is almoſt neuer called the God of iudgement: heare how hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimeth himſelfe: <hi>The Lord, the Lord ſtrong,</hi> there is one Epithite
<pb facs="tcp:9933:10"/> of his power; <hi>mercifull, gratious, ſlow to anger, aboundant in goodneſſe, and truth, reſeruing mercy for thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, forgiuing iniquity and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsion and ſinne:</hi> there are ſixe of his mercy. Then comes his iuſtice in puniſhing of offences: <hi>not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the wicked innocent, viſiting the iniquity of the Fathers vpon the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, vnto the third and fourth gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration:</hi> there he confines his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, hee ſayth vnto vs as he doth vnto the ſeas in <hi>Iob:</hi>
               <note n="(w)" place="margin">Iob. 38.11.</note> 
               <hi>Hither ſhalt thou goe, and thou ſhalt goe no further, here ſhalt thou ſtay thy raging waues,</hi> it ſhall not paſſe the fourth gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and that is more then Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie, if it come ſo farre, it is but at a high ſpring,<note place="margin">Exo. 20.5.6.</note> 
               <hi>vpon ſuch as hate him:</hi> but his mercy followes like a boundleſſe Ocean, <hi>vpon thouſandes of thoſe that loue him.</hi> Nay the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet tels vs that to puniſh, is with
<pb facs="tcp:9933:10"/> God a rare &amp; extraordinary work.<note n="x" place="margin">Eſa. 28.21.</note> 
               <hi>The Lord</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>ſhall ſtand as in as in mount Perazim, he ſhall be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry as in the valley of Gibeon, that hee may doe his worke, his ſtrange worke, and bring to paſſe his act, his ſtrange act.</hi> This is an act of iudgement, where you ſee that to puniſh, with him is an vncouth and ſtrange worke, an acte indeed, vnto which without compulſion of iuſtice, hee could not be drawne; hee is more loath to put out his hand for to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict a iudgement, then euer was <hi>Octauius</hi> to ſubſcribe his name to the execution of any publike offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, whoſe vſuall ſpeech was this,<note place="margin">Sueton.</note> 
               <hi>Vtinam neſcirem literas,</hi> I would to God I could not write. How oft doth miſerable man offend againſt his maker? ſurely if the iuſt man fall ſeuen times, then the wicked fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth ſeuenty times ſeauen times, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:9933:11"/> yet hee maketh his Sunne to ſhine vpon them both, he makes his rain to fall vpon them both, ſtill almoſt hee containeth the ſword of his iuſtice within the ſheath of his mercy: if in caſe hee bee enforced to draw it, hee is as it were touched with a feeling of that which the wicked ſuffer; heare himſelfe ſpeak, <hi>Therefore thus ſayeth the Lord of hoaſtes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1.24.</note> 
               <hi>the holy one of Iſrael, ah, I will eaſe me of mine aduerſaries, and auenge mee of mine enemies:</hi> it is a kind of eaſe to be auenged of thine enemie, and therefore God when the Iewes continue ſtill to prouoke him to his face, will eaſe himſelfe by inflicting his iudgements vpon them, <hi>I will eaſe me of mine enemies,</hi> but it comes with an <hi>(ah)</hi> or <hi>(alas)</hi> it is paine and griefe to him, hee is wounded to the very heart, his bowels are rowled and turned
<pb facs="tcp:9933:11"/> within him; a few teares might haue made him ſheath his ſworde, and deferre his puniſhments; the hiſtory of <hi>Ahab</hi> will proue as much, who was one that had ſolde himſelfe to worke wickednes, that <hi>prouoked the Lord God more then all the Kings of Iſrael that were before him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 16 30.</note> then <hi>Baaſha,</hi> then <hi>Omri,</hi> then <hi>Ieroboam the ſonne of Nebat that made Iſrael to ſinne,</hi> therefore the Lord ſends vnto him the Prophet <hi>Eliah</hi> telling him, that in the field where <hi>the dogges licked vp the bloud of Naboth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 21.19.21.</note> 
               <hi>they ſhould licke his blood alſo, and that he would wipe away his poſterity as one wipeth a diſh, when it is wiped and turned vpſide-downe. Ahab</hi> hath no ſooner rented his clothes at the Prophets words, then God repenteth him of what hee had threatened: <hi>Seeſt thou how</hi> Ahab <hi>is humbled before me?</hi>
               <note place="margin">verſe. 29.</note> a ſimple
<pb facs="tcp:9933:12"/> humiliation God wot, onely in outward ſhew, and yet it ſhall ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to reuoke part of Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt him, <hi>becauſe hee ſubmitteth himſelfe before me, I will not bring that euill in his dayes vpon his houſe. Niniuie</hi> had multiplyed her tranſgreſſions as the ſand vpon the ſea ſhore; ſhe had by her ſinnes blowne vp the coales of Gods an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger againſt her; but yet he will not come vpon her as a thiefe in the night to deſtroy her, ſhe ſhall haue <hi>fortie dayes warning,</hi> and if in the meane time ſhe will turne her plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into praying, and her feaſting into faſting, and by couering her ſelfe with ſackcloath, hide from his eyes her broade ſayles of pride, he will make it knowne vnto her, that hee was not ſo ready before, to lend a left eare of iuſtice to her cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſinnes, as he is now to affoord
<pb facs="tcp:9933:12"/> a right eare of mercy to the cry of her ſinners:<note place="margin">Ionah. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>hee will repent of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil that he had denounced againſt her, and will not doe it.</hi> The old world had ſo defiled the earth with her cruelties, and the ſmoake of her ſinnes did ſo fume vp to heauen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the noſtrils of God,<note place="margin">Gen. 6.6.</note> 
               <hi>that he was ſorry in his heart that euer hee had made man:</hi> yet hee will not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently deſtroy this wicked gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, there ſhall bee <hi>an hundreth and twenty yeares for repentance,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſ.</hi> 3</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee will purge this <hi>Augaeum ſtabulum,</hi> with a deluge of waters.</p>
            <p>Nay, ſuch is the neuer drying ſtreame of his mercies,<note place="margin">Ruffin hiſt. Eccleſ. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Cap. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> that for the righteous ſake, the wicked though they doe not repent, ſhall fare the better. God is not like to the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> who for the offence of a few, put all the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> to the ſword: but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:9933:13"/> (if without offence the Potter may be compared to the clay) like to that <hi>Perſian</hi> Generall,<note place="margin">Herod. lib. Plut. in Caeſare.</note> who ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red <hi>Delos</hi> becauſe that <hi>Apollo</hi> was borne there; or <hi>Caeſar</hi> who made the <hi>Cindians</hi> free men for <hi>Theopom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> his ſake: it was an opinion of the Heathen, that for one euill mans ſake, many good men were put to the worſe,
<q>
                  <l>— Pallas exurere gentem</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Virgil. <hi>1.</hi> lib AEn.</note>Argiuûm at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ipſos voluit ſubmergere ponto:</l>
               </q> 
               <hi>Pallas</hi> ouerthrew the whole nauie of the <hi>Argiues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vnius ob noxam &amp; furias Aiacis Oilei,</hi> for the ſinne of one man by name, <hi>Aiax</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Oileus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heſiod. op. &amp; dies.</note> and Πολλα<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> καὶ ξυμπασά πόλις κακοῦ ἀνδρὸς ἐπαυρεῖ, <hi>God puniſheth a whole City for one mans ſinne, and ſends vpon it</hi> Διμὸν ὸμοῦ καὶ λόιμον, <hi>famine and plague, for the ſinne of ſome particular,</hi> it is not ſo: God neuer puniſheth one
<pb facs="tcp:9933:13"/> man for anothers offences: if thou obiect vnto me, that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were plagued for <hi>Dauids</hi> treſpaſſe, I anſwere, <hi>Dauids</hi> ſinne did occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that puniſhment which the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> did iuſtly deſerue for their owne iniquities: for howſoeuer <hi>Dauid</hi> in reſpect of himſelfe (who deſerued more) called them ſheep, yet indeede they were <hi>Wolues in ſheepe skins:</hi> and verily in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, wee haue an euident de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of his mercies: for firſt, of three ſeueral puniſhments, he giues him leaue to chuſe which of them hee would: When <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> had choſen the Peſtilence for three dayes, indeede he ſent his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying Angell; but before his ſword was halfe drawne, hee puts it vp againe, and repenteth him of the euill, and abridgeth the time: Now we know that euery ſubſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb facs="tcp:9933:14"/> from his iudgements is a multiplication of his mercies, and how farre hee is from puniſhing the righteous with the wicked, let <hi>Sodome</hi> witneſſe, a ſinke of the fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thieſt ſinnes, a cage of the vnclea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt birdes, a denne of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedeſt theeues that euer the earth bredde: yet hee will not raſhlie come vpon her, but <hi>firſt he will goe downe and ſee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 18.21.</note> 
               <hi>whether they haue done altogether according vnto that crie which was come vnto him,</hi> &amp; if there can but fiftie righteous men bee found in fiue Cities, which was but for euery Citie ten, nay, if but for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nay, if but thirty, nay, if but twenty, nay, if but tenne can bee found amongſt them all, which was but for euery City two, he wil not deſtroy the City for thoſe mens ſake: when none can bee found ſaue iuſt <hi>Lot,</hi> hee will not
<pb facs="tcp:9933:14"/> ſubuert <hi>Sodome</hi> before hee bee brought out of the City, nay, hee will ſpare the whole City of <hi>Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar</hi> for <hi>Lots</hi> ſake: if good <hi>Paul</hi> bee in the ſhip, all that are with him,<note place="margin">Act. 27.</note> euen the barbarous Souldiers ſhall for his ſake come ſafe to land. But of all others (that I may end this point where I beganne it) <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> in my Text is moſt famous: whome the Lord doth ſo tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly compaſſionate, that if within her ſpatious walles, amongſt ſo many millions of ſoules, one righteous man could haue beene found, ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther amongſt the Nobles or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, or Prieſts, or People, hee would haue ſpared <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> for that mans ſake.</p>
            <p>And is this true? bee not then <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> diſmayed thou fainting and drou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping ſoule, whome the burden of thy ſinnes hath preſſed downe to
<pb facs="tcp:9933:15"/> the brinke of hell: is there ſuch a thunder-threatning cloud of Gods iuſtice ſet before thine eyes, that thou thinkeſt it impoſſible that the Sunne of his fauour ſhould pearce through it into thine heart? de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue not thy ſelfe, <hi>where ſinne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundeth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>there grace ſuperaboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth;</hi> thou art a fitte Subiect for God to worke vpon: where ſhould the Phyſitian ſhew his skill, but where the greateſt maladies doe raigne: and where can God better ſhew his mercy, then where is the greateſt aboundance of mans mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie? the deſperateſt diſeaſes that can befall the ſoule of man, dead Apoplexies, vncleane leproſies, dangerous Lethargies, remedileſſe Conſumptions, whatſoeuer they be, God can as eaſily cure them, as the ſmalleſt infection: and as he is able, ſo is he moſt willing to doe
<pb facs="tcp:9933:15"/> it, becauſe his mercy (as I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready proued) is his chiefeſt attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, and euery attribute of God, is the Eſſence of God, ſo that hee can no more ceaſe from his works of mercy, then the eye beeing well diſpoſed from ſeeing, or the fire from heating, or the heauen from mouing, or the Sunne from ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: hee that denyeth this is a Traytor to the king of Heauen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee gaine-ſayeth that ſtill wherin God eſpecially delighteth. There is no ſinne of it ſelfe ſo hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, but God can wipe it away: he will forgiue wicked <hi>Manaſſes</hi> aſwel as righteous <hi>Abraham</hi> 10000 talents as one penny.</p>
            <p>Suppoſe that all the ſinnes that euer were committed, from the murther of <hi>Caine</hi> to the treaſon of <hi>Iudas,</hi> laid vpon thy ſhoulders, there is no more proportion betweene
<pb facs="tcp:9933:16"/> them and Gods mercy then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Stillam muriae &amp; mare Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaeum</hi> betwixt a drop of brine and the <hi>Acgean,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cicero de ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus.</note> nay the great Ocean, the ſnuffe of the Candle and the light of the day, or a mote in the Sunne, and the Globe of the high heauen. Flie vnto the throne of grace, and though thy ſinnes were bloodie like Scarlet, he will make them as Wooll; and though thou be as Purple which is twice dyed, to wit in the Wooll and in the Cloath: Though thou bee dyed in the Wooll (the firſt lineaments of nature) with originall depraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in the Cloath (after thy natural perfection) with actuall tranſgreſſion, yet he wil make thee as white as the ſnow in <hi>Salmon:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.</note> he will bind all thy ſinnes <hi>in a bundell, and caſt them into the bottome of the Sea,</hi> hee will naile them vnto his
<pb facs="tcp:9933:16"/> Sonnes Croſſe, he <hi>will remoue them as far from thee as the Eaſt is from the Weſt, or the North diſtant from the South.</hi> No man euer begged an almes at Gods hand in faith, and returned empty. Heauen gates are neuer ſhut when penitent ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners knocke, there is a Maſter of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts in that Court, which is more ready to preferre thy petition vnto God, then thou canſt be to requeſt his helpe, and will he which for ten mens ſake would haue ſpared <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> and for one mans ſake haue paſſed by the crimſon ſinnes of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> who was moued with compaſſion at the hypocriticall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance of wicked <hi>Ahab,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoked his ſentence at the counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fait humiliation of proud <hi>Niniueh,</hi> ſtoppe his eares at the petition of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny penitent ſinner? doubt not but he will heare thy petition and giue
<pb facs="tcp:9933:17"/> his royall aſſent to that thou deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, though thou canſt but with <hi>Dauid roare and not ſpeake,</hi> or with the poore <hi>Publican</hi> vtter a ſhort and abrupt ſpeech <hi>O Lord be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto me a ſinner, &amp;c.</hi> or with <hi>Hezekiah Chatter like a Crane,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 38.14.</note> 
               <hi>and mourne like a Doue.</hi> Oh then flee vnto him <hi>as a Doue vnto the windowes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. 2.</note> hide thy ſelfe in the <hi>holes</hi> of the true <hi>rocke,</hi> put thy fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in Chriſts ſide there thou ſhalt finde both Oyle to ſoften and Wine to cure thy feſtered ſoule, cry mightily to God with <hi>Niniuch,</hi> ſay with <hi>Dauid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.13.</note> 
               <hi>I haue ſinned,</hi> morne with <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> weepe bitterly with <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 26.</note> fall downe at <hi>Ieſus</hi> his feete with <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 11.</note> ſay with blind <hi>Bartelmaeus</hi> in the Goſpell, <hi>O ſonne of Dauid haue mercy vpon me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 9.27.</note> And doubt not but God will bee mercifull vnto thy ſinnes, and make
<pb facs="tcp:9933:17"/> his fauourable countenance ſhine vpon thee.</p>
            <p>Againe is Gods mercy ſuch that hee will ſpare the wicked for the <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>2</label> righteous ſake? Here then yee ſonnes of <hi>Beliall,</hi> may learne this leſſon to ſpare the righteous for the wickeds ſake. I meane to cheriſh and to make much of all thoſe that feare the Lord, if for no other reaſon yet euen for this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuch men are often times a meanes to keepe away Gods iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from the euill doers, the chaffe ſhall not be burned as long as it is mingled with the wheat. <hi>Plutarch</hi> ſaith that in the ſacking of Cities ſuch houſes as were erected neare vnto a Temple, of any of the heathen Gods, were vntouched, when the reſt were ouerthrowne by the enemy: as long as a ſinner ſtandeth neare vnto a Temple of
<pb facs="tcp:9933:18"/> the liuing God, hee needeth not feare an ouerthrow. God could doe no hurt vnto the <hi>Sodomites</hi> as long as iuſt <hi>Lot</hi> was in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.</note> as he bleſſed the houſe of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Edom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 6.12.</note> 
               <hi>and all that he had becauſe of the Arke that was with him,</hi> ſo the bleſſings that fall vpon the wicked mans head, are becauſe of the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with whom he dwelleth; it was the encouragement that <hi>Caeſar</hi> gaue vnto the Boateman,<note place="margin">Phil in Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</note> when his Boate was almoſt ouer whelmed by the violence of the waues, in the Riuer <hi>Anius,</hi> that he ſhould not feare becauſe <hi>Caeſar</hi> was in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. And the beſt encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that can be giuen to the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, in the time of danger, is that ſome good man is in their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, then they may ſay as <hi>Michah</hi> ſaid when he had hyred a Leuite to be his Prieſt, <hi>now I know that the
<pb facs="tcp:9933:18"/> Lord will bee good vnto mee ſeeing a Leuite</hi> (a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that feareth the Lord) <hi>is with me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iud. 17.13.</note> and therefore at the leaſt in this one point, let them reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the iuſt man, <hi>which maketh much of them that feare the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 15. becauſe they are as it were Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers to keepe away the force of the blow,<note place="margin">Pſa. 106.23.</note> and with faithfull <hi>Moſes they ſtand in the gappe to turne away his wrathfull indignation, leaſt it ſhould deſtroy them.</hi> But if they ſeeke (as the cuſtome of ſo many is) by al meanes poſſible to deſtroy them, to trample them in the duſt and (as much as in them lyeth) to roote them out of the land of the liuing, that they may haue none to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trole them for their vnlawful deeds then they doe their beſt to cut a ſunder the thread that keepeth vp the ſword of vengeance, or <hi>Sampſon</hi> like to pull downe the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers
<pb facs="tcp:9933:19"/> vpon which their houſe ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and ſo to bring all downe vpon their heads.</p>
            <p>Againe is God ſo ſlow to anger, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>3</label> ſo vnwilling to reuenge? had hee rather ſaue one righteous man the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> puniſh a whole Citie, of ſuch as ſinne againſt him? Where bee the gallants of our dayes, who will not brooke the leaſt offence offered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them? Nothing ſhall waſh it away but the precious Blood, it is a diſgrace vnto me, an ignominie vnto my whole kindred, is that a diſgrace in thee which is an honor in god? For thy kindred I little ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of it. If thou canſt drawe it from the loynes of <hi>Adam,</hi> thou get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt nothing there but ſhame, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe thou canſt ſtep a foote higher (as <hi>Luke</hi> doth in the Genealogie of <hi>Ioſeph</hi>) and ſay that <hi>Adam was the Sonne of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 3.38.</note> if thou wouldeſt bee
<pb facs="tcp:9933:19"/> counted the Sonne of God, tread in his ſteps, walke as thou haſt him for an example. <hi>Be thou mercifull, as thy Father which is in Heauen is mercifull.</hi> For ſo doing thou ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thy ſelfe to be a ſparkle deriued from that infinite flame, a droppe taken from that bottomleſſe Oce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, it is remarkeable (which one ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth) that God hath giuen vnto Beaſts both weapons of defence and offence, the Lyon hath his Pawes, the Oxe Hornes, the Boare Tuskes, the Serpent his Sting, the Birds Clawes, the Fiſhes Skales, the very Hedg-hog is not without his Pricks: But man <hi>the excellencie of his dignitie, and the excellency of his Power</hi> (as <hi>Iacob</hi> ſpeakes of <hi>Ruben</hi>) he brings into the world ſmooth and naked,<note place="margin">Gen. 49.3.</note> in token that hee ſhould bee like vnto him, ſoft to anger ſlow to reuenge. <hi>Eſau,</hi> that was borne red,<note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 25:25.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:9933:20"/> and rough God diſinherited as a Monſter, and no true Child of his, but ſmooth <hi>Iacob</hi> hee acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to be his Sonne. The child of wrath is no Sonne vnto the God of mercy. How often doeſt thou ſinne againſt thy God? By thy blaſphemous oathes thou teareſt him, by thy hypocriticall holineſſe thou mockeſt him by thy vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thou poluteſt him, by thy ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogant pride thou diſdaineſt him, and ſpitteſt in his face. The leaſt treſpaſſe that thou committeſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, is no leſſe then treaſon againſt his royall perſon, and doth God for euery offence vn-ſheath his ſword againſt thee? <hi>Si quoties peccant homines ſua fulmina mittat Iupiter, &amp;c. If God ſhould in iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment puniſh euery ſinne vpon the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendor,</hi> where ſhould wretchedman be? now when God writeth thy
<pb facs="tcp:9933:20"/> ſinnes in duſt, wilt thou write thy Brothers in Marble? When he for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giueth thee ten thouſand tallents, wilt not thou forgiue thy Brother an hundreth pence? If thou wilt be indeede his Sonne, bee like vnto him, be pittifull, tender-harted full of mercy and compaſſion, if thou <hi>bee angry beware that thou ſinne not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4.26.</note> by ſpeedy reuenge, if thy wrath bee conceiued in the morning, and perchance increaſe his heate with the Sunne till mid-day, yet let it ſettle with the Sunne at after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone, and ſet with it at night,<note place="margin">1. Kings. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Let not the Sunne goe downe vpon thy wrath,</hi> if its conception bee in the night, vſe it as the harlot vſed her child, ſmother it in thy bed &amp; make it <hi>like the vntimely fruite of a woman which periſheth before it ſee the Sun,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal.</note> to this purpoſe remember that the Citizens of this <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> are at v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb facs="tcp:9933:21"/> amongſt themſelus, the ſtones of this temple are faſt coupled and linked together, the members of this Body as they are vnited in one head with the nerues of a iuſtifying faith: So are they knit in one heart with the Arteries of loue: The branches of this Vine as they are vnited with the boale (fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence they receiue nutriment) ſo haue they certaine tendrels whereby they are faſtned, and linked one to another. Now if without compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion thou ſeekeſt thy brothers hurt, thou doſt as it were deuide Chriſt, thou pulleſt a ſtone out of this Temple, thou breakeſt a branch from this Vine,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>AEneid.</hi> 3.</note> nay (more then ſo) thou cutteſt the Vine it ſelfe. <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gill</hi> tells vs that when <hi>Aeneas</hi> was pulling a bough from a mirtle tree to ſhadow his ſacrifice, their iſſued drops of blood from the boale tric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kling downe vnto the ground: at length he heard a voice crying vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb facs="tcp:9933:21"/> him thus <hi>Quid miſerum AEnea laceras iam parce ſepulto parce pias ſcelerare manus,</hi> the Poet tels vs that it was the blood of <hi>Polydorus Priamus</hi> his ſonne which cryed for vengeance againſt <hi>Polymneſtor</hi> the <hi>Thracian</hi> King which had ſlaine him, in like maner whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſoeuer thou ſeekeſt the ouerthrow of thy Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Brother, and haſt a deſire to reuenge thy ſelfe of him (as hee had to pull a bough from the Tree) thinke that it is not the branches but the Vine thou ſeekeſt to cutte downe. Thinke that Chriſt will count this indignitie done to his members as it were done to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Thinke that thou heareſt him cry vnto thee after this maner, <hi>iam parce ſepulto parce tuas ſcelerare manus,</hi> imbrue not thy hands in my blood, <hi>haud cruor hic de ſtipite ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat,</hi> it is not the branches thou fighteſt againſt,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iude.</hi> 9.5.</note> 
               <hi>Nam Polydorus e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go,
<pb facs="tcp:9933:22"/> I am Ieſus whom thou perſecuteſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Titus. 9.5.</note> I am now come neare to a point, which I haue preſſed heretofore in the other publique place of this ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,<note place="margin">At the Spit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle.</note> therfore I proceede no further, but turne aſide to my ſecond gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall point obſerued in this verſe, which was <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> miſery.</p>
            <p>The Tree is very fruitfull, and I am but a paſſenger, and therefore muſt be contented to pull two or three cluſters which I conceiued to be the ripeſt, and the readieſt to part with the boughes, which when I haue commended to your ſeuerall caſtes, I will commit you to God.</p>
            <p>Firſt the Paucity of true profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors <hi>(if ye can find a man, or if there be any.)</hi> Secondly, the place where. <hi>(In Ieruſalem.)</hi> Thirdly, that God will bring his iudgments vpon her becauſe of her wickedneſſe; not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed but neceſſarily vnderſtood.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9933:22"/>
            <p>From theſe three I collect three propoſitions; from the firſt, <hi>Gods flocke militant may conſiſt of a ſmall number:</hi> from the ſecond, <hi>There is no particular place ſo priuiledged, but that it may reuolt and fall from God:</hi> from the third, <hi>No place is ſo ſtrong, nor City ſo fenced, but the ſinnes of the people will bring it to ruine.</hi> Of theſe three in order, Gods holy ſpirit di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting me, and firſt of the firſt.</p>
            <p>God made all the world,<note place="margin">Propoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> and therefore it is great reaſon, that he ſhould haue it all to himſelfe: yea, and hee challengeth it as his owne right:<note n="c" place="margin">Hag. 2.8.</note> 
               <hi>The Golde is his, and the ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is his, and all the beaſts of the fielde are his, and ſo are the cattell vpon a thouſand hils:</hi> and the heauens are his, for they are his <hi>Throne,</hi> and the earth is his, for it is his <hi>footeſtoole,</hi> and the reprobate are his,<note place="margin">Pſal. Act. 749 Ierem. 25</note> for <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzer is his ſeruant,</hi> and as
<pb facs="tcp:9933:23"/> 
               <hi>Iuda</hi> is his ſo is <hi>Moab</hi> likewiſe: but in an other kind of ſeruice, in a word, <hi>The earth is the Lordes and all that therein is,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 24.</note> 
               <hi>the compaſſe of the worlde, and all that dwell therein,</hi> but not in that property, which is now ment for that belongs onely vnto men, and yet not vnto all, but to a few, which <hi>are appointed to be h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yres of ſaluation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.14.</note>
            </p>
            <p>God made all men, ſo that they are all his ſonnes by creation, but hee ordained not all to life, ſo that there is but a remnant which are his ſonnes by adoption: our firſt Father did eate ſuch a ſowre grape as did ſet all his childrens teeth on edge: by tranſgreſſing Gods commandement he loſt his birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and was ſhut out of Paradiſe, by committing treaſon againſt his Lord and King,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> his bloud was ſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and all his children were made
<pb facs="tcp:9933:23"/> vncapable of their fathers inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, but God (who is rightly tearmed the Father of <hi>all mercy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.3.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; God of all conſolation</hi>) as he purpoſed to ſhew his iuſtice in puniſhing the greater part of ſuch, as ſo gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly incurred his diſpleaſure: ſo on the contrary ſide, it was his good pleaſure to ſhew his mercy, in ſauing of ſome, though they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued as great a degree of puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as the other, and therefore it is a Parliament holden before all times, it was enacted, that the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall ſonne of God, the ſecond perſon in the Trinity, ſhould in the fulnes of time take vpon him mans fleſh, and ſuffer for our tranſgreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and gather a certaine number out of that <hi>Maſſe of corruption,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſtin.</note> wherein all mankind lay: theſe be they which ſhal follow the Lambe whetherſoeuer he goeth; theſe bee
<pb facs="tcp:9933:24"/> his <hi>people and the ſheepe of his paſture,</hi> theſe be they which haue <hi>this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue to be called the ſonnes of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 100. Gal. 4.1. Rom. 8.17.</note> 
               <hi>and the heires of God annexed with Chriſt:</hi> and theſe are they which I affirme to be often contained in a very narrow roome in reſpect of the wicked.</p>
            <p>There is much chaffe and little wheate, it is the wheate that God keepes for his garner: there are many ſtones, but few pearles: it is the Pearle which Chriſt hath bought with his bloud.<note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.</note> Many fowles but onely the Eagles bee good birds. Sathan hath a <hi>king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt but a little flocke,</hi> it is like to <hi>Bethleem</hi> in the land of <hi>Iudah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12.32. Mich. 5.2. Gen. 8.3.</note> but a little one amongſt the Princes of <hi>Iudah,</hi> it is like to <hi>Noahs</hi> floud, <hi>going and returning,</hi> like the ſea flowing and ebbing, or like to the Moone filling and waining, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:9933:24"/> ſometimes ſo Eclipſed and darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the earth, that thou canſt not perceiue, that Chriſt the ſonne of righteouſneſſe doth ſhine vpon it.</p>
            <p>The ſtory of Times will make this plaine, innumerous were the men of the old world, yet Gods flocke was onely contained in the family of <hi>Sheth,</hi> they onely were called the <hi>Sonnes of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 6.2.</note> afterward this flocke was compaſſed in a very narrow fold, in <hi>Noahs</hi> familie, it was encloſed in one Arke, and yet there <hi>was one Wolfe amongſt theſe few ſheepe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nat lupus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter oues. Ouid metam. lib: <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Thus it continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a very narrow compaſſe till <hi>Abrahams</hi> time, and ſo downeward till it beganne to multiply in the land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and afterward in the promiſed <hi>Canaan,</hi> as yet it was ſtill tied to one place, there was but one paſture for Gods ſheepe,
<pb facs="tcp:9933:25"/> the reſt of the world playde the harlot with other louers, and went a <hi>whoring after their owne inuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and in this one paſture there were more Goates then ſheepe, for though the <hi>number of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael were as the ſand vpon the ſea ſhore,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4.27.</note> 
               <hi>yet onely a remnant was to be ſaued.</hi> When the fulneſſe of time was come that God had ſent his ſonne made of a woman, this Moone did ſuffer ſuch an Eclipſe, as that the quickeſt eye could hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perceiue her: then ſhe beganne to recouer her light, for God broke downe the partition wall, and rent the vaile of the Temple, and made no difference betwixt the Iew and the Gentile, <hi>Tuos Niriuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> mihi nullo diſcrimene agetur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then Gods ſheepe <hi>brought forth thouſands and ten thouſands in the ſtreets,</hi> then the <hi>Vine ſtretcheth forth
<pb facs="tcp:9933:25"/> her boughes, vnto the riuer, and her branches vnto the lands end,</hi> then God gaue vnto his Sonne the <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then for his inheritance, and the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt part of the earth for his poſſeſsion.</hi> Yet then and euer ſince, the glea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of Satan haue bin more then the vintage of Chriſt. Yet take a ſuruey of the world, as it is at this day; deuide it into three parts with <hi>Ptolome</hi> or into fowre with ſome later writers, nay into ſixe or ſeuen with our laſt <hi>Geographers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Maginus.</note> and you ſhall not find much aboue one of theſe ſeauen which profeſſe Chriſt. Amongſt theſe ſeperate the ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxe from the heterodox, and you ſhall find that Chriſt is now almoſt baniſhed out of the world, ſo that if the ſonne of man ſhould now come,<note place="margin">Luk. 18.8.</note> he ſhould ſcarce <hi>find faith in the earth,</hi> the true profeſſion of the Goſpell, is confined in a little cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:9933:26"/> of the Northweſt, and in this corner remoue the Athieſts, and Hereticks, and Worldlings, and Neuters, and Hypocrits, how little will the remainder be after ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſubſtractions? And no maruell, for <hi>many are caled, but few are choſen,</hi> and <hi>broad is the way that leadeth to diſtruction.</hi> Gods ſheepe haue a little narrow path, but the Goates haue a beaten Cartway.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>1</label> This being ſo, it is ſtrange what <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ment to make ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, and multitude, to be a note of the true Church; eſpecially when he propoſeth to ſpeake of ſuch notes, by <hi>which it may be moſt eaſily knowne, and diſtinguiſhed from the falſe religion of the Iewes, and Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, and Pagans, and Infidels what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer:</hi> and therefore ſuch as are both<note n="g" place="margin">Notae de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent eſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priae non co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munes lib <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>2</hi> et poſtea in eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem cap. no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae variae inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parabiles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uera Eccleſia</note> proper and inſeperable, in reſpect of the Church; and againe
<pb facs="tcp:9933:26"/> 
               <hi>ſuch as thogh</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Non quidem efficiunt euidenter ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ipſam eſſe veram Dei Eccleſiam, ſed tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> efficiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t euidenter credibile De eccleſiae lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>they make it not euident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true,</hi> yet <hi>they make it euidently cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible,</hi> not only probable (for<note n="i" place="margin">Lutherano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum notae non ſunt vllo mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do, ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, nam non declara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t quae ſit vera Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia, ſe cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haeretic. niſi probabiliter lib eod. cap. <hi>2</hi>
               </note> that is the imperfection of our notes, if you will beleeue him) nay, <hi>amongſt thoſe which admit of the Scriptures, and Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories and wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the ancient fathers, faciunt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam euidentiam veritatis.</hi> Lord how plauſible a Doctrine would this haue beene vnto <hi>Ahab;</hi> how would it haue fitted his turne to plead for <hi>Baal?</hi> what meaneſt thou <hi>Eliah</hi> thus to trouble Iſrael? As though wee were all Idolaters and thou onely a true worſhipper of God? Conſider the matter aright, and thou ſhalt find what a weake ground thou ſtandeſt vpon, thoſe are the true worſhippers of God, who are the moſt in number, now thou art but one and the Prophets of <hi>Baal,</hi> are fower hundreth and fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb facs="tcp:9933:27"/> how pleaſantly would it haue ſounded in the eares of the Iewes, when <hi>Ieremiah</hi> thus propheſied? Behold (might they ſay) all the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants, of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> are againſt thee, and is the ſpirit of God departed from vs all to poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe thee? Thus <hi>Conſtantius</hi> diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with <hi>Libanus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> againſt <hi>Athanaſius</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Hoc orbis terrarum comprobat: quota tu pars es orbis ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum qui ſolus facis cum homine ſcelerato pacem orbis d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſoluis. Theod. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The whole world is of this Opinion, and what art thou that thou ſhouldeſt take part with a naughty fellow, and diſolue the peace of the world.</hi> If this obiection had bin vrged againſt <hi>Luther,</hi> when he firſt began to baite the Popes Bull, hee might eaſily haue anſwered in <hi>Athanaſius</hi> his words:<note place="margin">Athan. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. ad ſolita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian. vitam agentes.</note> 
               <hi>What Church is there now that doth openly adore Chriſt; if it bee godly it is Subiect to danger, for if there bee any that feare God (as indeede there are many euery where) they haue hid themſelues with
<pb facs="tcp:9933:27"/> Elias in Dens and Caues of the earth.</hi> But the example of the Iewes will not much mooue our aduerſarie <hi>quia non eſt eadem ratio populi Iudeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum et populi criſtianorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bellar. li. <hi>3.</hi> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Eccle. milit. cap. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> and might the Church of Chriſtians bee ſtill knowne, by the multitude of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, ſo that a man not yet reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in the truth, might bee guided by this marke to find her out, as the wiſe men by the Starre were dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted vnto Chriſt! Surely no,<note place="margin">Jdem. lib. <hi>4</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>for ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus initio fuiſſe multo p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uciores Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianos, quam eſſent Iudaii,</hi> what bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was ſhee in the time of thoſe ten bloody perſecutions which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured for the ſpace of three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares? when a man could no ſooner make profeſſion of his faith but hee was either <hi>killed with the ſword or burnt with fire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Alij flammis exuſti, alij fer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ro perempti, alij flagris verberati alij cru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iati patibulo, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>or drowned in the Sea, or ſtoned to death, or ſlaine quicke, or famiſhed with hunger, or
<pb facs="tcp:9933:28"/> thrust through with bodkins, or throwne to wild Beaſts, or pulled in peeces with Trees or wilde horſes, or boiled in lead, or made away with more exquiſite, and more Tragicall torments.</hi> (If that be poſſible) then the <hi>Perilli</hi> of our time haue inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to gratifie the Romiſh <hi>Phalleris.</hi> Come a little lower and compare the Church not with the number of the Gentiles, (which no Papiſt in the world can for ſhame deny to haue euer exceeded the number of Chriſtians) but with Heretikes, I meane not al ſorts ioyned togeher (for they will ſubſcribe to<note n="a" place="margin">Haeraetici ſunt per to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam faciem terrae, alij hic alij ibi alia ſecta in Africa, alia, hareſis in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riente Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt de paſt. Cap. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> the Church is euery where, and Hereſie euery where, but the Church is the ſame euery where, hereſie is not the ſame but moſt dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent) but only the <hi>Arians,</hi> which ſometimes haue ſo ouerſpread the whole Chriſtian world, as that if any had ſaid, <hi>Loe here is Chriſt or
<pb facs="tcp:9933:28"/> there is Chriſt,</hi> thou wouldeſt haue beleeued him. The Church was like a Sparow that ſitteth alone vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the houſe toppe, or like a Peli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can in the Wilderneſſe, and an Owle in the deſart: they counted themſelues the onely Catholikes, but the true Chriſtians they tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Sciſmatikes,<note place="margin">Auguſtine</note> calling them <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>annites,</hi> and <hi>Ambroſians,</hi> and <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natians,</hi> and <hi>Homouſians:</hi> Euen as the Papiſts at this day challenge the name of Catholikes, to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and call vs Lutherans, and Zuinglians, and Caluiniſts.</p>
            <p>They did not onely poſſeſſe the Church of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dria,</hi> &amp; <hi>Antiochia,</hi> &amp; <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and the reſt in the Eaſtern Empire, but paſſing thence into the North, &amp; from thence with the <hi>Gothes,</hi> and <hi>Vandals</hi> into <hi>Germanie</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> (yea into <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fricke</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9933:29"/> to) had infected all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in the Weſt. Which makes <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſay <hi>that the whole world gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and marueiled,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hierom. in dialog contr. Luciferia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos.</note> 
               <hi>to ſee her ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come am Arrian, an Arrian</hi> ſate in <hi>Peters</hi> chaire, the <hi>head of the Church</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Durand. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that</hi> great <hi>Melchiſedecke whoſe Prieſthood is not to be compared to any other, their</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Dominus deus noſter Papa. Ex trau. Ioh. <hi>22.</hi> vt citat Iuell.</note> 
               <hi>God and their Lord, the</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Durand. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pope</hi> himſelfe, rather then hee would die in the defence of the Goſpell, ſubſcribed to <hi>Arianiſme;</hi> ſurely the whole Body muſt needs goe wrong,<note place="margin">Liberius teſte. Athan. Epiſt. ad. Solitariam. vitam agen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes idem patet. ex preambulo. Concil. Nicen.</note> when the head did thus miſcary.</p>
            <p>This plague indured not for ſome ſmall moment (like the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonian</hi> Empire which was but <hi>a Flaſh and gone</hi>) but for the ſpace of three hundred yeares and vpward. Where was now the true Church amongſt the <hi>Arrians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bodin.</note> which op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugned the Doctrine of the <hi>Nicene</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9933:29"/> Synod in ſundry councels, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled the Orthodox Biſhops and enioyed their roomes, and inſtead of the true Chriſt worſhiped an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dole of their owne inuentions? or rather in a few miſerable and forlorne wretches, which remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in priſons and wilderneſſes, and Mountaines, and dennes, and Caues of the Earth, as was the caſe of the Church at that time, ſo was it in the time of <hi>Wicliffe</hi> and <hi>Huſſe,</hi> for then the Diuell had for a long time bin looſed, and Antechriſt was in the height of his pride, &amp; the light of the Goſpell was taked vp in the Aſhes of Popery,<note place="margin">Ποῦ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>οτε εἴσιν ὃι τὴν πενίαν ἡμέν ὁνεισζ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>οντει καὶ τῶν πλοῦτῶν. κομπάζοντες ὁι πλήθει τῆνεν ἐκ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>κλησίαν ὅριξοντες, καὶ τό βρο<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>χυ, διάπ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>τύ οντες ποίμνιον. Nazianz. in oratione con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Arria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nos.</note> in ſo much that that which <hi>Nazianzen</hi> ſpoke in the oration againſt the <hi>Arrians,</hi> might fitly haue bin applied againſt the Papiſts. <hi>Where be thoſe that obiect po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerty vnto vs, &amp; boaſt of their proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Eſtate,</hi> this is another marke of the Popiſh Church.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:9933:30"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Where be thoſe that define the Church to bee a multitude, and ſet at nought a little Flocke:</hi> and yet if multitude ſhould beare the bell away, the Papiſts ſhould not haue any ſuch cauſe of triumph, as they will beare the world in hand that they haue. There are at this day fowre Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the world (if the name of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion may bee giuen to them all) <hi>Iudaiſme, Paganiſme, Mahameta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianiſme:</hi> of all theſe <hi>Iudaiſme</hi> is the leaſt, but <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſme</hi> exceedeth all the reſt, <hi>Mahametaniſme</hi> (which is a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture craftily compoſed of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther three) both in largeneſſe of Countries, and multitude of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, goeth beyond all Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome: for it hath not onely ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it ſelfe in the whole <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Empire, and the large kingdomes of the great <hi>Sophi,</hi> but ſpreadeth
<pb facs="tcp:9933:30"/> abroad in many places of the vaſt dominions of <hi>Tartarie, Cathaia,</hi> &amp; <hi>China</hi> almoſt vnto the Eaſterne Ocean, and what it hath of later yeares gained in the weſt, wee feele partly in the miſerable diſtreſſe of <hi>Hungarie</hi> and <hi>Tranſiluania,</hi> and haue iuſt occaſion of greater feare, if the Lord out of compaſſion to his poore Church, ſhall not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrow the plots of that proud <hi>Senacherib,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Kin. 19.28</note> and put <hi>a hooke in his noſe, and a bridle in his lips, and carry him backe againe the ſame way that he came.</hi> Now for Chriſtianiſme, amongſt thoſe that profeſſe the name of Chriſt, there are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue a third part that are Papiſts: for the <hi>Ruſsians</hi> together with the Reliques of the Greeke Church, the <hi>Armenians</hi> and the Chriſtians that are vnder the Emperour of the <hi>Abaſsens,</hi> doe exceede the
<pb facs="tcp:9933:31"/> number of all thoſe, which holde the Principles of the Romiſh Church. The Proteſtants come not much behind them: for how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer within theſe hundred years, the Moone did ſuffer ſuch an vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall Eclipſe, that a man would haue iudged ſhe had loſt her light, and the Lords flocke was but like a few grapes after the Vintage is ended, <hi>here a grape and there a grape on the outmoſt boughes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Breui occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pauit doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Lutheri, non Soli mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta regna in partibus ſep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temtrionali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſed etia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad Indos excur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fa eſt. Bel. lib. <hi>3.</hi> de pont. Ro. cap. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note>Yet ſince it pleaſed God to ſtirre vp the heart of <hi>Martin Luther</hi> to ſtand at open defiance with the <hi>Italian Goliath which reuiled the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael of God:</hi> ſhee hath euery day recouered her light, the Goſpell that was then hid vnder a buſhell, is become like to <hi>Dauids</hi> Sunne, <hi>which commeth foorth as a Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome out of his chamber, and reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth as a Giant to runne his courſe:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9933:31"/> the profeſſors of the Goſpell haue wonderfully increaſed ſo that now <hi>their ſound is gone through the earth, and their words vnto the ends of the world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 90.4,</note> There is no place in the Globe of the earth, where Chriſt is profeſſed, which hath not ſome Proteſtants. <hi>Italy</hi> the very Center and ſinke of Popery, and the ſeat of the great Whore, when <hi>Iezabel</hi> hath done what ſhee can, in mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering the Lords Prophets, will affoord <hi>ſeuen thouſand men which haue neuer bowed the knees of their hearts vnto Baal.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>id. Bell. de Paul. Rom. lib <hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>21.</hi> Noſtris tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poribus Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana ſedes magna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniae par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem amiſit, Suetiam Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiam, Norue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giam, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam, &amp;c.</note> In <hi>France</hi> wee haue a farre greater number, in <hi>Germanie</hi> the <hi>maior</hi> part, almoſt all <hi>Polonie,</hi> all <hi>Denmarke, Swethen, Norway, Britaine,</hi> and all the Iſlands in the Northerne ſeas, which haue taken the militarie Oath to fight vnder Chriſts ſtandard. If theſe be not equall to them, yet conſider
<pb facs="tcp:9933:32"/> on eyther ſide ſuch as know the Principles of Chriſtian Religion, and can giue an account of their faith, and we haue a farre greater number, for the common people amongſt them are ſtupide &amp; blind, and doe no more vnderſtand the myſteries of their ſaluation then Pagans and Infidels, or thoſe in the Acts, who being demaunded of <hi>Paul,</hi> whether they had receiued the holy Ghoſt, made anſwere that they neuer <hi>heard whether there was an holy Ghoſt or no.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 19.2.</note> And little mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell for many of their Prieſtes doe no more vnderſtand their Maſſes, which they mumble dayly in their Churches; then <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood his owne voice. It is enough for them to belieue as the Church belieueth, though they know no more what that is, then did <hi>Bellarmines</hi> Collier, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:9933:32"/> demaunded what he belieued, (quoth hee) <hi>that which the Church beleeueth,</hi> being againe demaunded what that was, anſwered, <hi>the ſame which I belieue:</hi> Herein we will not thinke much that the Papiſts ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede vs: <hi>Bellarmine</hi> may giue good meaſure if he draw the dregs and all:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt: in</hi> Pſal. 39.</note> but <hi>Auſten</hi> will teach him another leſſon, <hi>Noli numerare tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas hominum incedentes latas vias, implentes craſtinum circum, ciuitatis natalem clamando celebrantes, ciuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ipſam male viuendo turbantes, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li illas attendere, multi ſunt, &amp; quis numerat, ſed pauci per viam anguſtam incedunt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt: hom: <hi>40.</hi> ad popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum Antio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chium.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> will teach him that not <hi>in numeri magnitudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, ſed in virtutis probitate conſiſtit multitudo.</hi> It was a prety ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geme of the <hi>Romaine</hi> Captaine, when his Souldiers were few in number, to make euery man draw
<pb facs="tcp:9933:33" rendition="simple:additions"/> a bough in the drie duſt, that ſo the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amnites</hi> (with which hee was to encounter) beholding them a farre off might beleeue that his Armie was greater then indeed it was: we are no ſuch daſtards as to be afraid of euery withered branch that can rayſe vp duſt into the ayre:<note place="margin">Liuius decad <hi>1.</hi> lib. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> if the Papiſts purpoſe to match vs with multitude, let them bring ſuch as haue ſome skill to handle their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall weapons.</p>
            <p>I end, ſeeing the Church is like vnto the Moone, ſometimes in a glorious ſplendour, ſometimes clouded with Schiſme, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time ſo darkened with the ſhadow of hereſie and ſuperſtition, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, that the eyes of <hi>Linceus</hi> can ſcarſe behold her.</p>
            <p>Seeing that the Papiſts at this day, cannot compare neyther with the number of Chriſtians (taking
<pb facs="tcp:9933:33"/> the name generally for all ſuch as profeſſe the name of Ieſus) nor with the Proteſtant Churches, if we take an account onely of ſuch as vnderſtand the Principles of their Religion:<note place="margin">Hic non te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netur nota marginalis quae nunqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> occurrit in li. Sent. P. Lamberti.</note> I ſee no reaſon why <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſhould make mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude a Note of the true Church; or if it were, why the Papiſts ſhould challenge it themſelues: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee may bee well cenſured with a <hi>hic magiſter non tenetur,</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iues de cauſis Co:|rupt: Art.</note> or <hi>nota quod haec nota nihil notat,</hi> it was onely to make vp the number of notes, that hee may number one Art, <hi>nam cum non proſunt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gula, multa iuuant;</hi> though they be of little force being ſeuerally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, yet if they bee all ioyntly taken, they will proue like<note n="t" place="margin">Plut Apoth.</note> 
               <hi>Seleucus</hi> his roddes, or like a <hi>threefold corde which is not eaſily broken.</hi> Indeede hee had need to bee ſtronger then
<pb facs="tcp:9933:34"/> 
               <hi>Hercules,</hi> that could cut off all the heads of <hi>Hydra</hi> at one blow: but a ſimple warriour taking one by one may make an end of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee bee wearied; for they are like to the tayle of <hi>Sertorius</hi> his horſe,<note place="margin">Plutar. in vita ſertorij.</note> which a valiant Souldier taking it all together, could not pull off, but a poore Skull pulling one hayre after an other had quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made it bare.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>2</label> Secondly, dooth Gods flocke ſometimes conſiſt of a very ſmall number? then it behoueth thee (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued Chriſtian) with greater di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to trie and examine thy ſelfe, whether thou bee compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in this number: for as in that vniuerſall deluge of waters, all were drowned that were not in <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke: ſo in the great floud of fire, which ſhall bee at the end of the world, all ſhall be ſwept
<pb facs="tcp:9933:34"/> away with a riuer of brimſtone, which are not of this flocke: it is a common ſaying, <hi>he ſhall neuer haue God for his father which hath not the Church for his mother,</hi> and hee ſhall neuer bee a member of the Church triumphant, which is not firſt of the Church Militant: firſt, then thou art to enquire whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thou bee of the true viſible Church; and this thou ſhalt know, by two markes; by the true prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the word, by the right vſe of the Sacraments, for where theſe two are performed according to the preſcript of Gods word, there muſt needs be a true church; this is ſomewhat, but it is not all: for what did it auaile <hi>Iudas</hi> to bee numbred amongſt the twelue? hee was in hell before any of the reſt came at heauen: all that are in the church bee not of the church:
<pb facs="tcp:9933:35"/> there are both good and bad fiſh in this net; there is wheat and tares in this field, Sheepe and Goates in this fold, thou muſt therefore goe further and examine, whether thou bee one of that Company, which God from eternity elected vnto life, and in time effectually cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth by his holy Spirit, and makes true members of his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt, which is the head of this body, whether thou bee of that flock which Chriſt <hi>calleth his garde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant</note> 
               <hi>his ſiſter, his ſpouſe, his loue, his doue, his vndefiled, which is the pillar and ground of truth,</hi> 1. Tim. 3.13. <hi>the body of Chriſt,</hi> Eph. 1.23. <hi>the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Lord,</hi> Eph. 2.21. <hi>which the gates of hell ſhall neuer preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt,</hi> Matth. 16 18. Here thou muſt exerciſe thy wits, this muſt be thy care to finde thy ſelfe in this little number, but how may this
<pb facs="tcp:9933:35"/> bee knowne? by the cauſe? that is the will and good pleaſure of God, which dwelleth in light that none can approach vnto. This is a bottomleſſe depth, who can ſound it? Neuer man looked into this Arke and liued: buſie thy braines about it, and when thou haſt done all thou canſt, thou art but like a flie about a Candle, which playeth ſo long with the flame,<note place="margin">Lipſius lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Con.</note> that at length ſhee burnes her wings and fals downe: and good reaſon it ſhould bee ſo: for it is enough for wretched man to bee of Gods Court,<note place="margin">Plut. in Theſ.</note> and it is too much to be of his Priuie Councell: thou muſt therefore doe as <hi>Theſeus</hi> did with the Labyrinth, thou muſt catch hold of the threeds end that hangs without the doore, and ſo by win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſteps come at length to the firſt cauſe. Seeing thou canſt not
<pb facs="tcp:9933:36"/> know it a <hi>Priori</hi> by the cauſe; thou muſt know it a <hi>poſteriori,</hi> by the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, an effect of Gods immutable decree, and an vndoubted marke (to let all others paſſe) of Gods child his Sanctification: for as on the one ſide it is certainely true, that <hi>without holineſſe of life, no man ſhall ſee God:</hi> Heb. 12.14. So it is as true on the other ſide, that <hi>hee which walketh not after the Fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.1.</note> 
               <hi>but after the Spirit is ingrafted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt</hi> and ſhall neuer be <hi>condem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned.</hi> So the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> holines of life is the true touchſtone, to trie whether thou be of this number: but here deceiue not thy ſelf, for there is a verbal ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines, and a Phariſiacall holines, and a <hi>Herods</hi> holines, and a popiſh holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and an Anabaptiſtical holines. The verball holineſſe is of ſuch as <hi>draw neere vnto God with their lips,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 29.13.</note> 
               <hi>but with their hearts are farre from
<pb facs="tcp:9933:36"/> him</hi> as the Prophet ſpeakes: the Phariſaicall holineſſe, is of thoſe which <hi>deuoure widdowes houſes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der colour of long prayers;</hi> and ſuch as will not leaue a mote on the outſide of their cappe, but neuer care how filthy it be within. The <hi>Herods</hi> holineſſe is of them which will quench the fire on the harth, and leaue it burning in the toppe of the chimney, will mende their leaſt faults, and let their worſt bee marring. The Popiſh holineſſe is in obſeruing humane traditions, and treading vnder foot the law of God. The <hi>Anabaptiſticall</hi> holines is of ſuch, as are well perſwaded of themſelues (though without all reaſon) but can neuer haue a cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable opinion of any others: they are troubled with a <hi>Noli me tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere, touch mee not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 65.5.</note> 
               <hi>come not neare me for I am holier then thou: but I
<pb facs="tcp:9933:37"/> ſay vnto thee, except thy righteouſneſſe exceede the righteouſneſſe of all theſe men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>thou ſhalt not enter into the Kingdome of Heauen:</hi> it is an other kinde of holines which thou muſt haue, if thou wilt aſſure thy ſoule that thou art one of Chriſts flocke: it is indeede in the tongue, but it proceedeth from an other foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine (the heart) and makes a man ſay with <hi>Dauid, thy wordes haue I hid within my heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> 
               <hi>that I might not ſinne againſt thee.</hi> It makes a man haue a carc to approue by outward actions vnto men, but much more to approue the cogitations of his heart vnto God: it ſtriues not to breake of ſome branches of ſinne (ſuch as may bee beſt forgone) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing the reſt, but it is moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere againſt thoſe ſinnes which are the ſweeteſt to man, becauſe ſuch ſinnes as are moſt pleaſant vnto
<pb facs="tcp:9933:37"/> many, are moſt vnpleaſant in the ſight of God. It will not ſticke cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritably to cenſure others: but it makes a man moſt ſharp in cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring &amp; containing his own ſinnes, it reſteth not contented with any one degree of perfection, but <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth that which is behind, &amp; ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoreth to obtaine that which is before,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>and followeth hard toward the marke for the price of the hie calling of God in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beloued in our beſt beloued Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, doe ye all deſire to bee fully aſſured that you are of that little number, whoſe names are written in the booke of life: I know you deſire it, for (alas) what comfort can a man haue in this life, though he ſhould be Monarch of the whole world, and to haue kings to lay their crownes before his footſtoole, if hee doubt what
<pb facs="tcp:9933:38"/> ſhall become of his owne ſoule? that of the heathen Emperour, <hi>animula vagula blandula que nunc abibis in loca, &amp;c.</hi> Though it be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by popiſh Diuinitie,<note place="margin">Verba mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entis Traia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni.</note> will be but a cold comfort to a Chriſtian on his death bed: hee ſhall neuer come in heauen that is not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of the way before hee goe hence. This is the beſt marke whereby you may aſſure your ſelues, that ye are already in the high way, euen your ſanctificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Oh then bee not (as to many are) like painted tombes, guilded without, rotten within; tippe not your tongues with godlineſſe, when your ſoules are full of gall and bitterneſſe. Beare not Bibles in your hands, and Mammon in your hearts. Let the remembrance of this, that holineſſe of life is the cogniſance of euery true member
<pb facs="tcp:9933:38"/> of Chriſts Church, be as it were a knife to cut a ſunder the cords of vanitie, wherewith Satan ſtriues to ſtrangle you, or to draw you headlong into hell and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Let it be as a ſpurre to pricke you forward in the courſe of idle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, aſſuredly howſoeuer my words may now paſſe away as a wind, and not ſinke into the hearts of many that ſhall heare them: yet <hi>Cum votat ille dies, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ouid Meta. lib. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> When thoſe muddie walles are readie to fall (and fall they muſt for all your daubing) there cannot a greater terror befall your conſciences (to make you feare that you are but rotten members at the beſt of Chriſts Church) then the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of an euill life: nor on the other ſide can there a greater com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort betide you,<note place="margin">Eccl. 12.8.</note> when <hi>your pitchers are ready to be broken at the ceſterne,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9933:39"/> then to aſſure your ſelues by your liues paſt (abounding with good workes which are the fruits of a iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying faith) that you are amongſt thoſe which God hath accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to be his children. For then you may go with greater deſires vnto your graues then a weary pilgrime vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to to his bed, aſſuring your ſelues that your ſoules ſhall bee tranſported into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, there to raigne with the holy Angels in eternall happineſſe, for euermore.</p>
            <p>The ſecond propoſition fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>No particular place is ſo priuiledged, but that it may reuolt and fall from God.</hi> If euer citie that was ſeated vnder the cope of heauen, had a Pattent from the God of heauen, for her perſeuerance in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, it was <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> for as of all the countries in the world, hee chooſe <hi>Iudea,</hi> ſo of all the cities of
<pb facs="tcp:9933:39"/> 
               <hi>Iudea,</hi> hee preferred <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> Sometimes his tabernacle was placed in <hi>Silo,</hi> but this hee diſliked,<note place="margin">Ioſh. 18.1.</note> and remooued vnto <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> as the onely place which hee had pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and culled out of all others to ſet his name there; according to that of the Prophet. <hi>He refuſed the Tabernacle of</hi> Ioſeph, <hi>&amp; choſe not the tribe of Ephraim: but he choſe the tribe of Iudah, euen the hill of Sion, which he loued, and there hee builded his ſanctuarie as an high palace, like the earth which he ſtabliſhed for euer.</hi> Pſal. 78.67.68.69. Thus he made a ſeat for himſelfe, <hi>an holy place, for the tabernacle of the moſt higheſt.</hi> Here was a Temple for <hi>the Lord, an habitation for the mightie God of Iacob,</hi> thoſe that ſhall but ſleightly peruſe the graunts and priuiledges which God hath promiſed this one citie, will thinke that it had beene as impoſſible for her to fall
<pb facs="tcp:9933:40"/> away, as for the found to be darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the midſt of heauen. <hi>The hill of Sion is a faire place, euen the ioy of the whole earth vpon the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide lieth in the citie of the great king, God is well knowen in her palaces, as a ſure refuge. Ieruſalem haue I choſen out of the tribes of Iſrael, to put my name in it for euer.</hi> 2. King. 21.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord hath choſen Sion to bee an habitation for himſelfe, hee hath longed for her, ſaying, this ſhall be my reſt for euer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 132.14.15.</note> 
               <hi>heere will I dwell, for I haue a delight therein. Heere was the ſeate of iudgement, euen the ſeate of the houſe of Dauid. To whom the Lord had ſworne by his holineſſe, that his ſeed ſhould endure for euer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 132.5.</note> 
               <hi>&amp; his ſeat ſhould be as the Sun before him: that he ſhould ſtand faſt for euermore, as the Moone, &amp; the faithfull witneſse in heauen.</hi> Pſal. 89. When the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites were yet in the wildernes,
<pb facs="tcp:9933:40"/> God told them by his ſeruant <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> that hee had appointed them a place in the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> where they ſhould all meete out of their ſeuerall tribes, and townes to offer their firſt fruits, &amp; to ſacrifice vnto the Lord: <hi>You ſhall ſeeke the place which the Lord your God ſhall chuſe out of all your tribes to put his name there, and thither you ſhall come, and ſhall bring your burnt offrings, &amp; your ſacrifices, &amp; your tithes, &amp; the offrings of your hands, and your vowes, &amp;c. And there yee ſhall offer before the Lord.</hi> Deut. 12. <hi>This was Ieruſalem, for thither the tribes came vp euen the tribes of the Lord, to teſtifie vnto Iſrael, and to giue thankes vnto the name of the Lord.</hi> Pſal. 122. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer here was there συνεδριον their chiefe Councell,<note place="margin">Sigon. de rep. haeb. lib. <hi>6.</hi> Cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> or high Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, (conſiſting of the king and princes of the people, to wit, the
<pb facs="tcp:9933:41"/> chiefe of euery tribe, and of ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Elders,<note place="margin">Gijon de reſp: haeb. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> and of the high Prieſt, with the Doctors of Law) in which all matters of greater moment were concluded, and vnto which (as vnto the Oracles of God) in dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult pointes, which could not be decided by the Iudges of particular Townes and Cities, they were to haue recourſe for the full determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation therof, according to that of the Prophet: <hi>If there riſe a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter too hard for thee to iudge be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene bloud and bloud, betweene plea and plea, betweene plague and plague, in the matters of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie within thy gates, then ſhalt thou ariſe, and goe vp vnto the place which the Lord thy God ſhall chuſe, and thou ſhalt come vnto the Prieſtes of the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites, and vnto the Iudge that ſhall bee in thoſe dayes and aske, and they ſhall ſhew thee the ſentence of iudgement
<pb facs="tcp:9933:41"/> and thou ſhalt doe according to that thing which they of that place (which the Lord hath choſen) ſhall ſhew thee, and thou ſhalt obſerue to doe according to all that they enforme thee,</hi> Deut 17. Beſide this, the law was there more diligently then in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces expounded; the Prophets did reueale Gods ſecrets vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and by thundering out the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of the law did ſtriue to weane them from their euill wayes, and by the promiſes of the Goſpell to wooe them vnto God: the <hi>Iebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites</hi> which before time God had permitted to dwell amongſt them; that they might be thornes in their eyes, and prickles in their ſides, were now extirpated,<note place="margin">Sigonius de rep: Haeb. li. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> ſo that they could not choke the word of God, which was ſowne amongſt them, and make it vnfruitfull. Was there euer City vpon the face of
<pb facs="tcp:9933:42"/> the earth, which had ſuch a Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as this? it was the Citie where God had promiſed to be reſident, where was the Arke of the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and the glorious Temple which <hi>Solomon</hi> had built at Gods appointment, where the Kings of <hi>Iudah</hi> had their abode, where the Law and the Prophets were dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently read and expounded vnto the people, where all points of dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie were handled, where was the Prieſtes Pallace, whether the whole land had recourſe out of their ſeuerall Tribes, as vnto the <hi>place where men ought to worſhippe:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 4.</note> it was a heauen vpon earth, and a type of that glorious City which is aboue: and is <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſo fallen from God, can there not one righteous man bee found within her walles? is the holy City be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come ſo wicked? is the faithfull
<pb facs="tcp:9933:42"/> Spouſe become a Harlot? are her Princes become Rebels, her Iudges Murtherers, her Golde droſſe, her charity oppreſſion, her ripeneſſe rottenneſſe, her almeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deedes al-miſdeedes? Hath the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie of ſinne ſo infected euery part of her body,<note place="margin">Iſai. 1.</note> that <hi>from the ſole of the foote to the crowne of the head, there is nothing whole therein, but woundes and ſwellings, and ſores full of corruption?</hi> What neede we goe further for prouing our concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for as hee ſpeakes in <hi>Tully,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cicero. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de orat.</note> 
               <hi>Ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this is enough, or I know not what will ſuffice:</hi> if you would haue <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picall</hi> Arguments after ſuch a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration as this: I could leade you through many places of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention, which would manifeſtlie confirme my aſſertion. I could ſhew you the Churches of <hi>Galla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia</hi> and <hi>Philippi,</hi> and <hi>Corinthus,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9933:43"/> which <hi>Paul</hi> had planted, <hi>Apollo</hi> and other Diſciples had watered, and God had wonderfully encrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, I could inſtance in <hi>Smyrna,</hi> and <hi>Pergamus</hi> and <hi>Laodicea,</hi> &amp;c. In which the Euangeliſt <hi>Iohn</hi> had ſo painefully laboured in <hi>Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople</hi> and <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and <hi>Nice,</hi> and <hi>Chalcedon,</hi> famous for the generall Councels, in <hi>Carthage,</hi> and <hi>Hippo,</hi> and other Churches of <hi>Affricke</hi> in <hi>Antiochia,</hi> the firſt Godmother of Chriſtians, and in a word, in all the Eaſterne and <hi>Affrican</hi> Churches, in which ſo many Worthies haue floriſhed. What is the cauſe of theſe particulars at this day? behold they are fallen, <hi>as though they had not been planted, as though the ſeede of the word had not beene ſowne amongſt them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 40.</note> 
               <hi>as though that ſtocke had taken no roote in the earth, the Lord hath blowne vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and they are withered, and
<pb facs="tcp:9933:43"/> the whirlewind hath taken them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way like ſtubble: the abhomination of deſolation</hi> (let him that heareth it, conſider it) <hi>ſitteth in their holy pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> which are now nothing elſe but as it were an <hi>habitation for Dragons</hi> and Courts for Oſtriches,<note place="margin">Phillip. Loni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerus de rebus Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cicis.</note> inſtead of the ſacred Bible, they haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained the blaſphemous <hi>Alcho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran,</hi> their <hi>Mophti Meizin,</hi> and <hi>Antippi,</hi> and ſuch Idolatrous <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometains</hi> haue gotten the roomes of the ancient Fathers.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> What? and are theſe alſo fallen? <hi>then let her that thinketh ſhe ſtandeth take heede leaſt ſhe fall.</hi> I meane that ſtrumpet which aduanceth her ſelfe aboue <hi>the ſtarres of God:</hi> which ſaith, <hi>I am, and none els,</hi> and ſings with <hi>Niobe in the port, Sum Felix,</hi> I am in a happie eſtate, and there ſhall no harme happen vnto mee; which with <hi>Laodicea</hi> thinketh that
<pb facs="tcp:9933:44"/> ſhe <hi>is rich and encreaſed with goods, and needeth nothing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reue. 3.</note> 
               <hi>whereas indeed,</hi> (as anon you ſhall heare) <hi>ſhee is wretched and miſerable, and poore, and blind, and naked. Niniue</hi> had ſuch a conceit of her ſelfe, and did ſo far preſume vpon her ſtrength, that ſhe thought it had beene im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for all the powers of the world to bring her vnder the hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. And therefore the Lord bids her looke vpon the ſtate of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> a ſtronger Citie then <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niue,</hi> and yet ſhe was deſtroyed. <hi>Art thou better</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>then No,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nahum. 3.8</note> 
               <hi>which was full of people? that lay in the riuers, and had the waters round about it; whoſe ditch was the ſea, and her wall was from the ſea E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopia and Egypt were her ſtrength, and there was no end:</hi> Put <hi>&amp;</hi> Lubin <hi>were her helpers, yet was ſhe carried a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and went into captiuitie.</hi> The
<pb facs="tcp:9933:44"/> ſame may be ſaid of <hi>Rome,</hi> (ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that none of theſe Cities which I haue laſt mentioned may paralele with her) is ſhee better then <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> which was ſeated vpon ſuch ſtrong bulwarkes, as alreadie hath bene mentioned: yet ſhe fell from God and moued the holy one of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to anger againſt her: graunt vnto her all that ſhee can claime (and ſhe will be ſure to lacke nothing for want of challen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging,<note place="margin">Thraſilaus apud Athen. Dipnoſ. li. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> for ſhee is not vnlike to him who could not eſpie a ſhip floa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vpon the ſeas, but preſently ſaid it was his) and more then all the Papiſts in the world can proue to bee her due, yet ſhee hath no more to bragge of, then had <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem;</hi> is ſhe the mother citie of all other and the Metropolis of all Chriſtendome? So was <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> in reſpect of the inhabitants
<pb facs="tcp:9933:45"/> of <hi>Iurie.</hi> Which at that time were the onely people which God had choſen. Are al others to appeal vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her as vnto their ſupreme iudge in matters of difficultie; ſo were <hi>Iewes</hi> vnto the high court of <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem;</hi> did <hi>Peter</hi> the <hi>prince of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, the porter of heauen gates,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue his chaire from <hi>Antiochia</hi> and placed it at <hi>Rome?</hi> ſo did the Lord his tabernacle from <hi>Shiloh</hi> to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> hath <hi>Rome</hi> the head or chiefe Biſhop of all Chriſtendom? <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> had the like, is ſhee the keeper and diſpenſer of the Lords treaſurie? So was <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> doth ſhe challenge a freedome for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuering in the truth? <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> had better grounds to do the like: and verily, as <hi>Rome</hi> doth at this day flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter her ſelfe with a falſe applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of vniuerſall promiſes,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.33.39 Pſalm.</note> So did <hi>Ieruſalem. Abraham is our father, we
<pb facs="tcp:9933:45"/> are the children of Abraham,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 49.10. Ier. 7.4.</note> 
               <hi>this is my reſt for euer: the ſcepter ſhall not depart from Iudea, nor a lawgiuer from vnder his feet: the temple of the Lord, the temple of the Lord, this is the temple of the Lord.</hi> All her ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles that ſhe can any way lay claim vnto, will not make her better then <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> which became ſuch an Apoſtatate, that not one godly man could bee found in her. So that ſhe cannot challenge any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiledge to her ſelfe from falling to the like wickedneſſe, that which happens to the one, may be fall the other, Vnleſſe ſhee can deale with the truth, as the old <hi>Romanes</hi> handled the goddeſſe <hi>victoria:</hi> who after they had wonne the field, vſed to clippe her wings that ſhe might not flie away.</p>
            <p>But what neede we ſtand of the poſſibilitie, when the act proueth
<pb facs="tcp:9933:46"/> it. A certaine man, walking on his way, while hee looked not ſo well to his feet, as he ſhould haue done, fell into a pit: when diuers of his acquaintance came by, and ſaw his miſchance, they began to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire one after another, how hee fell thither: What a queſtion is that ſaid he, you ſee that I am fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, thinke rather of ſome meanes how to helpe me vp againe. We neuer need make queſtion, whither and how <hi>Rome</hi> could reuolt and fall from Chriſt; certaine it is, ſhe is fallen; and well it were for her, if ſhe could bee holpe vp. When <hi>Philip</hi> told <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> that hee had found the <hi>Meſsiah, of whom it was written in the Law, and in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> and told him who it was, viz. <hi>Ieſus of Nazareth: Nathaniel</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at it, and ſaid; <hi>Can any good thing come out of Nazareth?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 1.47.</note> If
<pb facs="tcp:9933:46"/> any ſhall wonder that there ſhould be any defect in <hi>Rome,</hi> which ſo many ages hath bene counted the mother &amp; nurce of true religion: I anſwere him as <hi>Philip</hi> anſwered <hi>Nathaniel, Come and ſee.</hi> When thou art an eye-witneſſe of all her abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, thou wilt ſubſcribe to his teſtimonie, who at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming away, bad her thus adew: <hi>Roma vale vidi, ſatis est vidiſse reuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, cum leno meretrice ſcurra cinoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus ero.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt confeſſe, that when firſt I made choice of this portion of Scripture, I did not intend to haue played vpon this ſtring with my leaſt finger. But now that I haue met <hi>Rome</hi> in my high way, I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not chuſe, but (by your patience) ſpeake a word vnto her before we part, eſpecially, when I conſider how ready ſhee is to diſgrace all
<pb facs="tcp:9933:47"/> ſuch as will not drinke of her Cyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean cups. How ſhe ſendeth her panders amongſt vs to get her moe cuſtomers, &amp; his pedlers to ſel her deceitfull wares. How buſie ſhe is in hanging vp her ſpider-webs to catch our Engliſh butterflies which haue neither wit to auoide them, nor ſtrength to break them; and what paines ſhe taketh in dec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king her ſelfe, and in painting her vglie wrinkled face, that ſhee may allure. <hi>Men deſtitute of vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding,</hi> to forſake their firſt loue, and commit follie with her. There was a time when <hi>Rome</hi> was a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Church,<note place="margin">Prou. 7.7.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> giueth her this teſtimonie, that<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>her faith was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed throughout the whole world.</hi> Shee was (as ſome ſay) the chiefe, ſeat for one of the foure Patriarks.<note n="b" place="margin">Praefac. in Concil. Nice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num <hi>1</hi> ſedes, Romanoe. <hi>2</hi> Alexandriae. &amp; Cant <hi>6.</hi> Antiqua Conſuetudo. &amp;c.</note> or rather of equall dignitie with the others, Her approbation
<pb facs="tcp:9933:47"/> was deſired in ſundry Councels, as one more incorrupt then the reſt,<note place="margin">Quia vrbis Romae paril. eſtres.</note> by reaſon that ſhe was not ſo ſhaken with Sciſmes and Hereſies, as were the Eaſterne Churches, ſhe was an <hi>Aſylum</hi> for many which were perſecuted for the teſtimonie of Ieſus Chriſt: this ſhe was, and this is all that ſhee can boaſt her ſelfe off at this day. Which when ſhe hath done, ſhe is no better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe degenerous ſpirits of Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie and Gentrie, who when they haue nothing in themſelues wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy the leaſt commendation, will digge vp the old roote whence they ſprang. But
<q>
                  <l>Si vita labat, perit omnis in illa,</l>
                  <l>Gentis honos cuius,<note place="margin">Ouid.</note> laus eſt in origine ſola.</l>
               </q> Hee leaneth vpon a rotten ſtaffe, which hath nothing to ſpeake for him ſaue his dead Progenitors ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. If any man thinke I doe her
<pb facs="tcp:9933:48"/> wrong, may it pleaſe him to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare her with the ſtate of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in the time when <hi>Ieremie</hi> propheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: the ſinnes of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> were eyther in doctrine and matters of Religion, or in conuerſation and manner of liuing: for the former, it is as much (if not more) corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at this day in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, then it was then amongſt the Iewes. The <hi>Prophets</hi> there<note n="c" place="margin">Ier 5.31.</note> 
               <hi>Propheſied lies:</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Cap. 23.24</note> 
               <hi>God ſent them not, and yet they ranne, he ſpoke not vnto them, and yet they propheſied</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Cap. 14.14.</note> 
               <hi>euen a falſe viſion, and the dreames and deuiſes of their owne hearts:</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Romaniſts doe this or no: thoſe impious aſſertions which they maintaine againſt the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches (for oppugning whereof,<note n="f" place="margin">Vid. Lind: li. <hi>4.</hi> Cap. <hi>100.</hi> et petrum a Soto contra Brentium.</note> many holy Martyrs haue with their beſt bloud dyed the skirts of the purple hoare) may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently
<pb facs="tcp:9933:48"/> witneſſe. What ſhall I tell you of their prayers for the Deade, their Sacrifice of the Maſſe, their communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vnder one kinde, their vowes, their forbidding of Maria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, their Indulgences, their Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie, their workes of Superero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, and a number moe, by which like<note n="g" place="margin">Act. 14.25.</note> the Siluer Smithes of <hi>Diana,</hi> they haue gotten their goods? all which make a goodly ſhow of holineſſe, to ſuch as are blinded with the miſtes of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, by reaſon that the candle of the word is couered vnder a Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhell, and locked vp in the cloſet of an vnknowne tongue, but bring<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 105.</note> 
               <hi>Dauids Lanthorn</hi> to trie them and you ſhall finde that when they are viewed in the light, they wil proue like Gloe-wormes, and Toade-ſtooles, more like to any thing then
<pb facs="tcp:9933:49"/> that which they were taken for: or like<note n="i" place="margin">Solimus.</note> the Apples of <hi>Sodome,</hi> which make a goodly ſhow a farre off, but if they be once touched, they will preſently fall into duſt; or like thoſe<note n="k" place="margin">D. D. in his preface vpon Euclid.</note> Mathematicall Showers, which in the twilight ſeeme to bee golde or precious ſtones, yet where the light comes, proue nothing but lime &amp; ſand: then their prayers vnto Saints wil proue but <hi>much babling:</hi> their Images <hi>teachers of lies,</hi> their forbidding of mariages, <hi>doctrines of Deuils:</hi> their Purgatorie fire borrowed from the ſuperſtitious Ethnicks, to keepe their Kitchins hoat, their Maſſes, maſſacres of Soules, their Holy-water, Cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixes, Reliques and Ragges of Saints, &amp;c. <hi>beggarly rudiments,</hi> baſe Marchandiſe not worth the cheapning: this they themſelues know full well, and therefore if yee
<pb facs="tcp:9933:49"/> aske theſe <hi>Luci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ugae ſcripturarum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. de re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrectione Carnis. Perſius. Eckius Pig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hius contro. <hi>3.</hi> de ſcriptura. Ludov. Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus quat. in orat. hab. in Concil. Trid. vide Chem. in exam. Concil. Trid, et Iuel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum in defen. apol. Cap. <hi>19.</hi> et. <hi>20.</hi> Si quis habe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t interpretatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem Romanae Eccl. deal q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>co ſcripturae etiamſi nec ſciat nec in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligat an aut quomodo eum ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris Conueniat. habet tamen ipſiſſimum dei verbum, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius: de expreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo dei verbo.</note> what warrant they haue from the Oracles of God,
<q>Romulidae Satyri quid diâ Poemata narrant?</q> They will tell you they haue it by tradition, or the Church hath or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned it: or it is not needefull to bring Scripture for a ground of their Poſitions: which it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſome of them to call a <hi>Leſbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an rule, and a noſe of waxe, and a blacke Goſpell, and inkie Diuinitie, and a dumbe Teacher, and a dead and killing Letter.</hi> Indeede, if they can wreſt any place of Scripture though it be contrary to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the holy Ghoſt, yet it muſt bee taken for ſound Diuinity, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as a great Cardinall ſpeakes: If any man haue the interpretation of the Romiſh Church, of any place of Scripture, although hee know not whether it agree with
<pb facs="tcp:9933:50"/> the word of God or no: yet it is not to be doubted, but hee hath the very word of God. Thus muſt theſe expoſitions goe for ſound Diuinitie, marke them and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them with Iewiſh gloſſes: <hi>Drinke yee all of this,</hi> that is not all, but ſome, to wit, the Cleargie, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage is honourable amongſt all men,</hi> not all, but ſome, the Laietie: <hi>Caſt not pear es before ſwine:</hi> that is, ſuffer not the people to reade the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in a known tongue:<note place="margin">Pſal. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Thou haſt put all things in ſubiection vnder his feete,</hi> that is, vnder the Popes feet: <hi>The fiſhes of the Sea,</hi> that is the Soules in Purgatorie, <hi>The beaſts of the land,</hi> that is the men of this world,<note place="margin">Antoni: in Sum. part. <hi>3.</hi> tit: <hi>2 2.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The fowles of the heauen,</hi> that is the ſoules of the bleſſed which the Pope hath canonized, <hi>Here are two ſwords,</hi> that is, the Pope hath the managing of both ſwordes,
<pb facs="tcp:9933:50"/> Ciuill and Eccleſiaſticall, an expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition not altogether ſo harſh, as that which<note n="n" place="margin">In his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſement to Pope Paul the Fift tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netians.</note> 
               <hi>Baronius</hi> brought of late, to proue that the Pope had au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority not onely to feede Chriſts Sheepe, but alſo to puniſh with death ſuch as reſiſt his Papal digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie: becauſe hee which ſaid,<note n="o" place="margin">Ioh. 21.</note> 
               <hi>Peter feede my ſheepe,</hi> ſaid alſo,<note n="p" place="margin">Act. 10.13</note> 
               <hi>Ariſe Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and kill:</hi> if he had preſſed the text a little further, hee might by the ſame Argument haue proued his holy Father to bee an <hi>Anthropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phagus</hi> or <hi>Caniball,</hi> becauſe it is not ſimply ſayde, <hi>Ariſe Peter and kill,</hi> but <hi>Ariſe</hi> Peter <hi>kill and eate,</hi> vnleſſe hee had <hi>Bellarmines</hi> wit,<note place="margin">Bellar. de Rom. Pont. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth the Popes Supremacy, not from the firſt word <hi>kill,</hi> but from the ſecond word <hi>Eate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the maine fault in Religion, which haſtened Gods iudgements vpon <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> was her idolatrie:
<pb facs="tcp:9933:51"/> Shee changed her God:<note n="r" place="margin">Ier. 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>She for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke the fountaine of liuing waters, and digged vnto her ſelfe euen broken pits which would hold no water: ſhee played the harlot vpon euery high mountaine, and vnder euerie greene tree:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Shee ſayde vnto a tree, thou art my Father, and to a ſtone, thou haſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten me.</hi> Whether <hi>Rome</hi> goe not beyond her in this particular, he that hath but halfe an eye may plainely ſee,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgill. Aene. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>
               <q>
                  <l>Cur natos toties crudelis tu quoque falſis,</l>
                  <l>Ludis imaginibus? —</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Wee doe not reade of many Idols that were famous amongſt the Iewes, there was <hi>Aſhtereth</hi> the God of the <hi>Sidonians;</hi> &amp; <hi>Milcome the abhomination of the Moabites,</hi> and <hi>Chemoſh</hi> the abhomination of the children of <hi>Ammon,</hi> and <hi>Baal,</hi> and a few more: but the Idols which Papiſts haue inuented are ſo
<pb facs="tcp:9933:51"/> many, that <hi>Rome</hi> can ſcarſe finde roome for placing them: Shee is more like to the old Gentiles, who did acknowledge one chiefe <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter,</hi> — αναξ ανδρωντε θεωντε,<note place="margin">Hominum rex atque de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum.</note>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And</hi> Iupiter omnipotens, qui res ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Deum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>
                  </l>
                  <l>aeternis regis imperiis:</l>
               </q> But hee had three hundred vnder him which they worſhipped as gods:<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>arro.</note> though the Papiſts acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge one ſupreame power, yet are there three hundred to whom they performe that worſhippe which is due onely vnto God, and as they had twelue which they counted greater gods, which <hi>Ennius</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth in theſe old verſes,
<q>
                  <l>Iuno, veſta, Minerua, Ceres, Diana, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus, Mars.</l>
                  <l>Mercurius, Iouis, Neptunus, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ulcanus, Apollo.<note place="margin">Extant apud Apulerum. et Natalem Comitem. Sen. na. quaeſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>41.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </l>
               </q> Whome they hold to be of Gods Priuie Councell: but many leſſer gods and goddeſſes for particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb facs="tcp:9933:52"/> purpoſes, as for their Waters, <hi>Lympha,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>arro. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de re Ruſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca.</note> for her Gardens, <hi>Pomona</hi> for their grounds, <hi>Terminus,</hi> &amp;c. So the Papiſts haue the twelue Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, which (with the <hi>Platoniſts</hi>) they vſe as Mediators betweene them &amp; the high God, vnto which they haue added the Virgine <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> thinking eſpecially by her inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion to haue their deſires; as the <hi>Troians</hi> in the Poet vſed the medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of <hi>Venus</hi> to obtaine fauour of <hi>Iupiter.</hi> Now for particular mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, there is ſcarſe any thing but they haue a God or Goddeſſe for it: When they are in feare of the plague they pray to <hi>Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lutherus in Decalog.</note> againſt the falling ſickneſſe to <hi>Valentine,</hi> againſt ſodaine death to <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi> againſt the Ring-worm to <hi>Anthonie.</hi> Now then as <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras</hi> from the print of <hi>Hercules</hi> his foot in the games of <hi>Olimpus,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9933:52"/> did collect the bigneſſe of his whole Body. So from theſe few things which haue beene ſpoken, you may gather how farre <hi>Rome</hi> hath declined from her former pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and how well ſhee may para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lell with <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in my Text. I might take occaſion to ſpeake of that preheminence, which the Pope chalengeth ouer all Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Kings (Gods immediate De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties on earth) by reaſon of a ſuppoſed Authority giuen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Peter,</hi> whoſe ſucceſſour hee pretenteth himſelfe to be, the very ſame argument in ſubſtance, by which the Turke claimeth the Weſterne Empire, becauſe hee ſucceedeth <hi>Conſtantine:</hi> or he that married <hi>Tullies</hi> wife, laid claime to his learning, becauſe he had mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried his executor: all Princes muſt hold their ſcepters from him, all
<pb facs="tcp:9933:53"/> nations muſt crouch downe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and all kingdomes muſt doe him ſeruice: Heere <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> dare not ſtand out in compariſon with <hi>Rome:</hi> her hie Prieſts were neuer come to that height of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudencie, as to ſet vp their heades aboue the Lordes annointed. When <hi>Tiberius</hi> obſerued the baſe ſeruitude which the <hi>Romanes</hi> vſed towards him: hee could not chuſe but cry out,<note place="margin">Tacitus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>O homines natos ad ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitutem,</hi> hee that conſidereth how vilely &amp; ſeruilely, ſhe which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time was the Empreſſe of the world, dooth obey him which is ſtiled a ſeruant of ſeruants, he may well vſe <hi>Tiberius</hi> his words: or thoſe of the Poet,
<q>
                  <l>Roma tibi quondam ſuberant domini dominoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</l>
                  <l>Seruorum ſerui nunc tibi ſunt domini.</l>
               </q> but this is only by the way. From her religion, let vs come to her
<pb facs="tcp:9933:53"/> conuerſation and manner of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was as corrupt in life, as ſhe was in religion:<note n="z" place="margin">Ier. 7.9.</note> 
               <hi>She did ſteale, murder, and commit adulterie, and ſweare falſly.</hi> Her inhabitants,<note n="a" place="margin">Cap. 6.13</note> 
               <hi>from the leaſt vnto the greateſt, were giuen to couetouſneſſe, and from the Prophet vnto the Prieſt, they all dealt falſly.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Cap. 2.34.</note> 
               <hi>In the wings was found the blood of the ſoules of poore innocents:</hi> How farre <hi>Rome</hi> goeth beyond <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> euen in this alſo we may haue a little taſte in our holy Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Catholikes, the remainder of the Romiſh Church, and the only true profeſſours (if ye will beleeue them) of the ancient faith in this kingdome: but trie them by the works of regeneration (the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall bodie of true Chriſtianitie) and you ſhall find, that in propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Gods Sabbath, in ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and blaſpheming, in lying and
<pb facs="tcp:9933:54"/> cozening, in drunkenneſſe and whoredome, in oppreſſion, and all vnconſcionable dealings, they are for the moſt part, the very ſcumme and excrements of this land. And why ſhould they make conſcience of theſe ſinnes,<note place="margin">Venalia Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae temlpa, ſacerdotes altaria ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra, coronae, ignes thura preces Coelum eſt venale de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſque.</note> ſeeing their holy mother is as it were a faire or roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Exchange, where any ſinne may bee bought at a reaſonable rate. Nothing more common then what doe you lacke, or what will you buy, &amp;c. A pardon for your ſinnes paſt, or for any ſinne you ſhall hereafter commit? a tol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leration for common Stewes, for, (but I dare not name it) a diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for inceſtuous marriages, or any thing els, you ſhall haue it if you can agree for the price: ſhall I ſay all in a word, Shee is a hell of impieties,<note place="margin">Reu. 18.2.</note> 
               <hi>a habitation of diuels, and the hole of all foule ſpirits, and a cage
<pb facs="tcp:9933:54"/> of euery vncleane and hatefull bird.</hi> And therfore I leſſe maruaile why Friar <hi>Mantuan</hi> ſhould bee ſo bitter againſt her corruptions in his time.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Sanctus ager ſcurris venerabilis ara cinaedis,</l>
               <l>Seruit, honorandae diuum Ganimedibus aedes.<note place="margin">Mantuane.</note>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>And he ſaith further, <hi>Nulla hic arcana reuelo,</hi> It was no ſhriuing ſecrets the Fryar did diſcloſe, but ſuch things as all the world could witneſſe to be true. <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernardus. lib. <hi>4.</hi> de Conſiderato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ad Euge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium.</note> is more ſharpe againſt the abuſes of his time (though the rotten hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours were but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in gathering) when he complaineth that the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous, Luxurious, Ambitious, Inceſtuous, Sacreligious, and all ſuch helliſh Monſters did flocke to Rome, to get a warrant from the Apoſtolicke Sea, for their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. And that they made no more conſcience of Sinning, then
<pb facs="tcp:9933:55"/> theeues after they haue robbed a man by the highway, are afraid to deuide the ſpoile. <hi>Curia tua recipere bonos magis, quam facere conſueuit,</hi> (he ſpeakes vnto the Pope) <hi>mali enim illic non proficiunt ſed boni deficiunt.</hi> I intend not now to lay open her monſterous cruelties and bloody maſſacres, of ſuch as truely profeſſe the Goſpell of Chriſt, in which point ſhe doth very well reſemble (Shall I ſay) <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> which <hi>killed the Peophets &amp; ſtoned them that were ſent to her?</hi> nay, rather old <hi>Rome</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Nero as often as the Emperor gaue commandement that any ſhould be ſlaine or baniſhed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tacitus. lib. <hi>14.</hi> Annal. quoties fugas &amp; caedes iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit princeps, toties, predijs actae: quaeque rerum ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darum olim nunc publicae cladis inſignia fuere.</note> 
               <hi>ſo often</hi> (ſaith <hi>Tacitus) did they giue thankes vnto God: and thoſe things which in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer time had beene notes of ſome proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous ſucceſſe, were now the enſignes of publike ſlaughter.</hi> Is not this her cuſtome at this day? are there any
<pb facs="tcp:9933:55"/> bloody butcherings of Chriſts flocke, any cruell murthering of Chriſtian Princes, by Romiſh Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſites, but it ſhall bee receiued at <hi>Rome</hi> with Bonefires and Hymnes in moſt triumphant manner? all which things when I conſider, I am fully reſolued that a learned Diuine of later yeares, doth not ſpeake of any malitious humor, when hee ſaith that there bee three points of diuinity,<note place="margin">Caluinus lib. <hi>4.</hi> Iuſtit. ca. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> (he calleth them <hi>Capita arcana Theologiae</hi>) which go current in <hi>Rome. The firſt, that there is no God: the Second, that whatſoeuer is writen of Chriſt is lyes and deceits. The third, that the Doctrine of the reſurrection and of the laſt iudgement is merely fabulous,</hi> now then this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the caſe of that great and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Citie, wee may well collect, that her horrid deſolation and fearefull downefall is at hand. <hi>For
<pb facs="tcp:9933:56" rendition="simple:additions"/> there is no ſtate ſo ſtrong, no Citie ſo fenced, but the ſinnes of the people will bring it vnto diſtruction,</hi> which is my third and laſt Propoſition out of the ſecond generall branch of my text, whereof I am now by your patience to intreat.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Propoſit.</hi> 3</note>That Kingdomes and common wealthes haue their periods and downefalls, is a concluſion which the premiſes of all former ages doe demonſtrate; learned <hi>Athens,</hi> ſtately, <hi>Sparta</hi> rich <hi>Babylon,</hi> victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Carthage,</hi> ancient <hi>Troy,</hi> proude <hi>Niniue,</hi> and a thouſand more haue numbred their yeares: and at this day haue no ſtronger fence then Paper walls, to keepe their names from obliuion, the great enemy of antiquitie. Now for the true cauſe of their ſubuerſions, it is a truth, which the greateſt wiſards of this world, after much ſtudie, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb facs="tcp:9933:56"/> ſerious co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſultations which na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture could neuer find out. The <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picures</hi> attribute it to fortune the <hi>Stoicts</hi> to deſtinie, the <hi>Pythagorians</hi> to numbers. Which laſt opinion <hi>Plato</hi> made ſuch reckoning of, that he will haue numbers to bee the ſole cauſe of the tranſmutations of common wealths. Whoſe words bee ſo Aenigmaticall,<note place="margin">Plato. lib. <hi>8.</hi> de rep. Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro. lib. <hi>7.</hi> Epiſt ad Atticum.</note> that <hi>Tullie</hi> makes them a Prouerbe, and <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilius Ticinus</hi> inuocateth not <hi>Oedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus</hi> but <hi>Apollo</hi> to vnfold them.<note place="margin">Ariſt. <hi>5.</hi> lib. pollit. cap. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> (who of all others com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth neareſt vnto the trueth) makes the cauſe to be a diſharmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie in the body politicke, as too much wealth of ſome few, the great miſerie of many, iniurie, feare, &amp;c. I little maruell that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Philoſophers ſhould ſhoote ſo wide, when Chriſtians haue ſo groſſely miſtaken their marke. <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:9933:57"/> how wittie is hee in pleading for numbers?<note place="margin">Bodin Math. hiſt. cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> what vertue doth he attribute to 7. or 9. or 12. and the ſquares and cubiques. How doth he ſhift himſelfe to proue his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion ſound, by inſtances of the moſt comon-wealthes that haue bene hitherto in account, adding, or detracting yeres at his pleaſure, from the calculation of the beſt Chronologers, to make the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſquare or cubique, or ſpherical, or at the leaſt, ſome way conſiſting of 7. or 9. or of three rootes or ſquares. <hi>Cardanus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cardanus.</note> hangeth all vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the taile of the greater beare. The common ſort of Aſtrologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, referre it to the planets and ſtarres, making ſuch a ſcheme at the firſt foundation of any Citie, which made <hi>Varro</hi> (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth) ſo earneſt with <hi>Taruncius Firmanus,</hi> to enquire the oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb facs="tcp:9933:57"/> and aſpect of the planets, when <hi>Rome</hi> was firſt ſituated, thinking hereby to coniecture how long that Empire ſhould endure. <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernicus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Copernicus.</note> will haue the conuerſion &amp; motion of the centure of his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aginarie excentricle circle (which circle according to him, is not cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the heauens motion (for the heauens in his opinion are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moueable) but by the earth, which he will haue to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually whee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led about, to be the cauſe of theſe alterations of Common-wealths. Thus while they groped in the darke, they miſſed their marke,<note place="margin">Gen. 19.</note> as the <hi>Sodomites</hi> did <hi>Lots</hi> doore, <hi>and while they profeſſed themſelues wiſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.22.</note> 
               <hi>they became fooles.</hi> And little mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, <hi>for the wiſedome of this world is fooliſhneſse with God:</hi> None of all theſe haue happened on the true cauſe,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.</note> 
               <hi>it is the ſinnes of the people
<pb facs="tcp:9933:58"/> which bringeth euery common-wealth to ruine.</hi> And how can it be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe? for if thou lay more weight on the roofe, then the pillars can ſupport, the houſe muſt needes fall. Now ſinne is of ſuch an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable weight, that no houſe nor Citie, nor Common-wealth can ſtand vnder it, but it will preſſe it downe, it is a burden to the whole earth, and makes it <hi>reele to and fro,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 24.20.</note> 
               <hi>and ſtagger like a drunken man:</hi> it is a burden to all the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.22.</note> and <hi>maketh them grone and trauell in paine:</hi> it is a burden to God himſelfe, which makes him crie out in the Prophet againſt the <hi>Iewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 2.13.</note> 
               <hi>That they had preſſed him with their iniquities, euen as a cart is preſſed with ſheaues:</hi> it lay ſo heauie vpon Chriſts ſhoulders, that it made him <hi>ſweat drops of blood,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 22.44.</note> This burden of it ſelfe ſo heauie, like a
<pb facs="tcp:9933:58"/> malefactor that is preſſed to death, cries for <hi>more weight,</hi> to preſſe the ſinner to the pit of hell: it cals to heauen for the <hi>burden of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 23.</note> that is, for vengeance to be inflicted vpon the impenite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſinner, God in regard of his patience, and long ſuffring, is ſaid to haue leade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heeles, hee commeth ſlowly euen againſt his will to puniſh, but in reſpect of his iuſtice, he is ſaid to haue yron hands. He ſtriketh with a witneſſe, when once hee begins to ſmite in his proceedings againſt the ſinnes of men, he hath a double method ſometimes, (and this method is moſt vſuall when he proceedeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſinnes of his children) he comes to them as he came to <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 19.</note> Firſt he ſendeth a <hi>mighty ſtrong wind,</hi> to blow downe the tall Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dars, and caſt them to the ground, as <hi>Paul</hi> was, before he was conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.
<pb facs="tcp:9933:59"/> Then an <hi>Earth-quake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts 24.26.</note> to ſhake the flintie rockes, I meane the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie hearts of men, &amp; to make them tremble, as <hi>Felix</hi> did, when <hi>Paul</hi> diſputed of the iudgment to come, then <hi>a fire</hi> to burne vp the ſtubble, and conſume the bryars, and then (when theſe forerunners, like <hi>Iohn</hi> Baptiſt haue prepared a way for the Lord) he comes himſelfe, <hi>in a ſoft voice,</hi> the gratious and ſweet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the Goſpell, to ſeale a pardon to ſuch, as by the former Iudgments are deiected and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled. And this may bee tearmed Gods <hi>Ordo compoſitiuus:</hi> Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times (and this is more vſuall, eſpecially when hee proceedes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wicked) hee taketh a contrarie courſe: Firſt, he comes in a <hi>ſoft and ſtill voyce,</hi> to wooe them to himſelfe: But when they harden their hearts, and
<pb facs="tcp:9933:59"/> will not bee reclaimed from their euill wayes; then at length he will ſend a <hi>fire to deuoure them,</hi> and an Earthquake and mighty ſtrong wind, to <hi>ſcatter them away like chaffe from the face of the earth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 1.</note> &amp; to blow them downe euen in the bottome of hell; and this I may fitly call Gods <hi>ordo reſolutiuus;</hi> it is ſayd of <hi>Alexander,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Q. Curtius.</note> that when hee beſieged a certaine City, hee helde out a Lampe, proclaiming a pardon to as many as would yeeld themſelus before the Lampe was burned: ſo the Lord firſt holdeth out the Lampe of his word, whereby hee calleth them to ſubmit themſelues, and giues them a time to delibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate; if in the meane time they doe not yeeld, nothing remaines but death and deſtruction: it is ſtoried of <hi>Tamberlaine</hi> the <hi>Scythian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Stephani. Epi. in Herod.</note> that whenſoeuer hee beſieged a City,
<pb facs="tcp:9933:60"/> firſt hee diſplayed a white flagge in token of mercy, if they would yeeld themſelues, the ſecond day a redde flagge threatening blood becauſe they did not in time ſubmit themſelues, if they continued vntill the third day, then came out his blacke flacke menacing vtter ruine and deſolations; this is Gods Methode. Firſt he ſets out his white flagge of peace; if this bee not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, then comes his red flagge of correction, though not of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: if this will take no place with them, then he ſets out his blacke flagge,<note place="margin">Virgil lib. <hi>6.</hi> Aeneid.</note> 
               <hi>bella horrida bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> nothing but death and deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Downe with it, downe with it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> euen to the ground, tribulation and anguiſh, fire and brimſtone, ſtorme and tempeſt, this ſhall bee their porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to drinke.</hi> Its long before he be moued to anger, but if the coales
<pb facs="tcp:9933:60"/> of his wrath bee kindled; O Lord God how terrible will this flame be! it will licke vp the ſea like duſt, and melt the mountains like waxe, and burne to the very bottome of Hell, ſo that nothing in the world will quench it, but the bloud of the Lambe, and the ſtreaming teares of vnfained repentance: caſt your eies to the time of old, <hi>for wee are:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 8.9.</note> 
               <hi>but men of yeſterday, and our dayes on earth are like a ſhadow,</hi> as <hi>Bildad</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in <hi>Iob,</hi> and you ſhall finde my concluſion proued by the occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of all ages. <hi>Sodome</hi> that fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and plentifull Citie, which was for beauty and pleaſure <hi>like the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of God, or as the valley of Egypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene. 19.</note> 
               <hi>as thou goeſt vnto Zoar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gene. 13.10</note> if the ſtinke of her ſinnes aſcend into heauen, ſhall bee conuerted into a ſtinking Fen, for an euerlaſting remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of her iniquity.<note place="margin">Deut. 3.3.</note> 
               <hi>Iericho a
<pb facs="tcp:9933:61"/> goodly place, a City of Palme trees, a</hi> fenced City, <hi>whoſe walles reached vp to heauen:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn 6.21.</note> if ſhee be withall a ſinnefull and an idolatrous City, ſhee and all that is in her, both man and woman, young and olde, Oxe and Aſſe, ſhall bee vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed. <hi>Babylon,</hi> which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ariſt. Polit.</note> for the greateneſſe cals rather <hi>a Region then a City, the Empreſse of the earth,</hi> the Princeſſe of Cities, <hi>the glory of Kingdomes, the beauty and pride of the Chaldeans, which ſaid, I ſit as Queene, I am no widdow, and ſhall ſee no mourning:</hi> If ſhee conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued in her ſinnes, ſhall bee <hi>as the deſtruction of God in Sodome and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 13.</note> 
               <hi>it ſhall not bee inhabited for euer, neyther ſhall it bee dwelled in from generation to generation, but Zim ſhall dwell there, and their hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſhall bee full of Ochim, Oſtriches ſhall dwell there, and the Satyrs ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:9933:61"/> dance there, and Iim ſhall cry in their Pallaces, &amp; Dragons in their pleaſant places: ſo that a man ſhall bee more precious then gold, euen a man aboue the wedge of the gold of Ophyr:</hi> It is not her powerfull ſtate, nor rich Citizens, nor ſtrong walles, nor high Towers, nor magnificall buildings, that ſhall free her from Gods puniſhing hand: nay, <hi>Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem in my Text,</hi> the Vine that Gods right hand had planted, the Citie of the Great King, the holy place of the Tabernacle of the moſt high, <hi>the beauty of Iſrael, the glory of Nations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lament. 1.</note> 
               <hi>and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſses of prouinces,</hi> if ſhe will not bee awaked from her ſinnes, ſhall not be much better then the deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Sodome</hi> and the miſerable deſolation of doleful <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> her walls ſhall bee turned into heapes of duſt, her houſes conſumed, her
<pb facs="tcp:9933:62"/> Temple burned, her treaſury emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, her in habitants killed: <hi>Quis Cladem illius vrbis quis funera flaetu explicet.</hi> What heart is ſo flinty which will molt into teares, when it ſhall thinke of the miſerie which did twiſe befall this one Citie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now all</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">1. Cor. 10.11.</note> 
               <hi>theſe puniſhments came vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe. </seg>1</label> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for an enſample and are written to admoniſh you vpon whence the ends of the world are come,</hi> that you ſhould bee armed and warned, that you ſhould ſee, and fore-ſee, before the time be paſt,<note place="margin">Cicero. Phil. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>vt quorum facta imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamini eorum exitum per horreſcatis, that if you tread in their footſteps you ſhould reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber their downfals,</hi> God is the ſame God ſtill, he is as ſtrong as euer he was, he is as iuſt to reuenge as euer hee was, his arme is not ſhortned, his ſtrength is not aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>his wrath is not turned away from ſinne, but his hand is ſtretched
<pb facs="tcp:9933:62"/> out ſtil.</hi> Sinne may bud in the ſpring but it withereth before Harueſt: it may flowriſh for a time, but god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe endureth vnto the end. When the wicked thinketh him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the ſureſt, when he ſaith vnto his ſoule, <hi>Peace, Peace,</hi> and <hi>Soule, take thy reſt.</hi> Euen then there is but one ſteppe betweene him and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction: beleeue the kingly Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, he ſpeaketh it of his owne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, <hi>I my ſelfe haue ſeene the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly in great proſperity,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 37.36.37</note> 
               <hi>and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing like a greene bay tree;</hi> what followeth, <hi>I went by, and loe, he was gone; I ſought him, and his place could no more be found.</hi> Behold his countena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, he is but as the graſſe vpon the houſe top, which withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth before it bee pluckt vp,<note place="margin">Pſal 73.18.</note> or as the <hi>ſound vpon the water,</hi> or as a <hi>garment freted with mothes: O how ſuddenly doth he fade, periſh, and
<pb facs="tcp:9933:63"/> come to a fearefull end: euen as a dreame vaniſheth when as one awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. in vitae Pyrrhi. idem in vita Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nib.</note> It is noted of <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> and <hi>Hanniball,</hi> that they could quickly conquer a Citie, but they could neuer keepe that which they had once ſubdued. I little maruaile, that the wicked haue great facility in heaping vp of riches, but I ſhould thinke it ſtrange, if they could keepe them till the third ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration. Their wealth is like a ſnowball, gathered in the fall, not without labour and cold fingers: and anon after it is melted with the Sunne, or waſhed away with the raigne. But alas, alas beloued, I may heare take vp the Prophets complaint.<note place="margin">Iſa. 53.1.</note> 
               <hi>Who will beleeue our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port?</hi> my words ſeeme vnto many, as <hi>Lots</hi> Sermon did to his ſonnes in-law, when hee foretold the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of <hi>Sodome, who ſeemed as though he had mocked,</hi> Gen. 19.14.
<pb facs="tcp:9933:63"/> Giue mee leaue a little to ſpeake plainely: I came not to ſing vnto you <hi>a gloria patri</hi> without <hi>a ſicut erat,</hi> to flatter you with a ſmooth tale, as to lay pillowes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your elbowes, whereby you may ſecurely ſleepe in your ſinnes, <hi>Multi ſunt Placentini, &amp; Landen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes pauci Veronenſes, many come hither from</hi> Placentia, <hi>and</hi> Landa, <hi>but few from</hi> Veron. I doubt not but yee will all with your tongues confeſſe my Propoſition to be true, but the practiſe of the moſt denyeth it: <hi>it is the ſins of the people that bringeth euery common wealth to ruine.</hi> Euery one wil ſay as much, but yet in our practiſe wee hold an other ſtrange Axiom that goeth for currant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs: <hi>it is the ſinnes of the people that vpholdeth euery Common wealth:</hi> conſcionable and true, and faithful dealing, which my Prophet
<pb facs="tcp:9933:64"/> as I ſuppoſe, nameth, by <hi>executing of iudgement</hi> and <hi>ſeeking of the Truth,</hi> is like an Almanacke out of date, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man hath found out a new way, both to maintaine and better his eſtate, this old way is to farre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout. The blood-ſucking Vſurer, inſtead of lending and expecting nothing againe, a leſſon which our Sauiour would haue him to take out, if hee looke for the true trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, doth eat and conſume his nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Brother, euen as <hi>Pharaos</hi> leane and il-fauored Kine deuoured the other. This is the way hee taketh to ſupport his houſe, God loues not ſuch an Arethmatician as ſpendeth his whole ſtudy about <hi>Multiplication,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Regula falſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis.</note> and the <hi>Rule of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood,</hi> and can neuer learne, the <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe</hi> of Diuiſion. The Lawyer who ſhould employ his beſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in vniting the knots of the
<pb facs="tcp:9933:64"/> law, and ſhould bee an <hi>Atropos</hi> to cut off the thread of controuerſies betweene man and man: feedeth his Client with golden hopes, and ſugred wordes, and in the meane time like <hi>Lacheſis</hi> draweth in length the thread of contention, vſing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary delayes, and poſting of the matters from Court to Court, Tearme to Tearme, yeare to yeare, not vnlike the cogging Surgeon, who in hope of greater gaine doth poyſon the wound, that it may be longer in curing, or (if I may vſe a homely compariſon) like the waggiſh Boy in the ſtreetes, who when hee ſeeth two dogs ſnarling and grinning one at another for a bone, is neuer at reſt till (for his owne pleaſure, but little for their profite) hee hath brought them a <hi>rictu ad morſum,</hi> to trie their right by their teeth, til at length the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker
<pb facs="tcp:9933:65"/> bee enforced to reſigne vp his right to the ſtronger: this is a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall plot to maintaine his eſtate.</p>
            <p>The Citizen that liueth on his trade, is like to the idolatrous Iewes in the Pſalmiſt, which worſhip the Images of <hi>Canaan; Canaan</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth a Marchant, and what is the Marchants Image (ſaith <hi>Luther</hi>) but <hi>Denarius</hi> the Croſſe. This hee maketh ſuch reckning of, as that he careth not for making ſhipwracke, not of a craſed, wodden veſſell, but of a good conſcience, ſo that hee may obtaine it: hee ſelleth dayes and months, and yeares at a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er rate then his beſt ſtuffes; if his wares bee too light, falſe ballances muſt make vp the weight, if too bad, too deare, a falſe oath muſt make a mends for both. The coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try Landlord (for though I ſpeake in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> yet I do not doubt but
<pb facs="tcp:9933:65"/> ſome of euery quarter of <hi>Iudah</hi> doth heare mee, whome the Lord hath endowed with ample poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions that hee ſhould bee as it were <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> an vpholder of his Country, a maintainer of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, a ſcourge of vice, a protector of Religion, a ſhelter for the diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to defend them from the rage of oppreſſors, as the<note n="a" place="margin">Xenocrates apud Aelia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. var. hiſt. lib. <hi>13.</hi> cap. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> Philoſopher did the Sparrow that fled into his boſome from the talentes of the Hawke. What doth he? he rayſeth his rentes, wringeth his Tenants like ſpunges, ſhaketh by ſome new deuiſe the ancient cuſtome; if this will not ſerue his turne, he farmeth out his liuings (eſpecially in ſuch a yeare as this, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhould breake his bread to the poore at his owne dores) and taketh a roome in this City, or ſome other, where he may liue with much eaſe, little charges, and ſmall credite, this he counteth
<pb facs="tcp:9933:66"/> an eſpeciall meanes to hold vp his eſtate.</p>
            <p>If I haue beene in the boſomes of many of you, blame your ſelues, for mine owne part I may truly ſay to euery particular that thinketh himſelfe touched, as our Sauiour ſaide to the woman that was taken in Adulterie;<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.11.</note> 
               <hi>Hath no man condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thee? neither doe I.</hi> Marry, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all I adde that of <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3.20.</note> 
               <hi>If thine owne conſcience condem not hee, God is grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then thy conſcience, and knoweth all things;</hi> and therefore I diſmiſſe thee with that ſpeech of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſpoken to the Criple, that was newly reſtored to his feet; <hi>Goe thy way and ſinne no more,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 5.14.</note> 
               <hi>leſt a worſe thing come vnto thee.</hi> What ſhall I ſay more? Runne through each particular Eſtate and calling, and you ſhal find by the practiſe, thogh not of all, God forbid that I ſhould thinke ſo, I know there are in euery
<pb facs="tcp:9933:66"/> profeſſion which make a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience of their wayes, and in all their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ſet God before their eyes, yet of the moſt part, that fraudulent and deceitfull dealing, or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnlawfull meanes, is thought the moſt expedite and beaten way for ſupporting them. Few will let this conceit ſinke into their heads, that ſinne is the meanes that bringeth euery Eſtate to ruine, the Preacher may tell them as much, but they will belieue him at their leaſure; in the meane time, they wil ſtill runne on their olde <hi>Bias;</hi> the husbandman may labour in weeding thoſe grounds, but ſtill they bring forth briars to entangle and nettles to ſting others: the Gardner may buſie himſelf in pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thoſe vines, but ſtill they bring forth ſowre grapes, ſuch as will ſet the teeth of Gods children on edge. Gods ſhepheards may
<pb facs="tcp:9933:67"/> watch continually about their flockes;<note place="margin">Ier. 2.</note> yet <hi>like ſwift Dromidaries they runne by their wayes, and like the wilde Aſſe vſed to the wilderneſſe, which ſnuffeth the wind by occaſion at her pleaſure,</hi> as the Prophet ſpeakes; they canot bee kept from going a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtray. Euery one can bee angry if his worldly purpoſe be croſſed ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo little, but few or none will ſay with <hi>Dauid; it greeueth me when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſee the tranſgreſſors, becauſe they keepe not thy law:</hi> Many can weepe and commend plenty of teares, when any worldly calamity doth befall them, but few or none can ſhed one teare, <hi>Miſere terendo ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los</hi> (as he ſpeaks in the Comedy) for their ſinnes, much leſſe weepe bitterly as <hi>Peter</hi> did,<note place="margin">Math. 26.</note> or haue their eyes guſh out with water, becauſe other men keepe not Gods lawes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> with <hi>Dauid</hi> many will ſing to <hi>the Viole, and inuent to themſelues inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb facs="tcp:9933:67"/> of muſicke like</hi> Dauid <hi>as the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites did.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 6.5.</note> But few will ſay with him,<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.143.</note> 
               <hi>All my delight is in thy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements;</hi> Many will ſay, with thoſe good fellowes, <hi>Come &amp; bring wine, and wee will fill our ſelues with ſtrong drinke, and to morrow ſhall be as this day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 56.12</note> 
               <hi>and much more abundant</hi> But fewe or none will ſay with thoſe good profeſſors, <hi>Come &amp; let vs goe vp to the mountaine of the Lord, and to the houſe of the God of Iacob, and he will teach vs his lawes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>and we will walke in his paths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I thinke I cannot truely ſay with <hi>Hoſea,</hi> that <hi>the Lord hath a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie with the inhabitants of this land, becauſe there is no knowledge of God in the land.</hi> For our heads are not ſo <hi>ſicke,</hi> as our <hi>hearts</hi> are <hi>heauie:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1.5.</note> I meane our heads are not ſo void of knowledge, as our hearts are of obedience, but I dare boldly ſay, that which followeth: <hi>By ſwearing
<pb facs="tcp:9933:68"/> and lying, and killing, and ſtealing, and whoring,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>they breake forth, and blood toucheth blood.</hi> Wil you heare the iudgements annexed in the ſubſequent words: <hi>Therefore ſhall the land mourne, and euery one that dwelleth therein, ſhall be cut off.</hi> This is a terrible curſe, &amp; he that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in heauen, ſtill auert it from vs, but yet it is a concluſion which the Lord vſeth to inferre vpon ſuch premiſes.</p>
            <p>Giue me leaue ro repeat a para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vnto you,<note place="margin">Iſa. 5.1.2.3. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>My beloued had a vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard in a very fruitfull hill, and he hedged it, and gathered the ſtones out of it, and hee planted it with the beſt plants; and hee built a Tower in the midſt, and made a winepreſse therein.</hi> The Prophet in that place appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it to the land of <hi>Iudah, Surely the vineyard of the Lord of hoſts, is the land of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>and the men of</hi> Iudah, <hi>are his pleaſant plants:</hi> me thinkes I
<pb facs="tcp:9933:68"/> may not vnfitly apply it vnto this Iſland. Surely the vineyard of the Lord of hoſts is the land of <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,</hi> and the men of this land are his pleaſant plants, <hi>Now therefore, O ye inhabitants of this and, iudge I pray you, betweene him and his vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, what could he haue done vnto it, that hee hath not done?</hi> Hee hath planted it with his own right hand, hee hath ſo hedged it about with his heauenly prouidence, that the wild boare out of the woods can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not roote it vp, nor they that goe by, pull off his grapes. Hee hath watered it moſt abundantly with the dew of heauen: he hath gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſtones of Popery and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition out of it; he hath ſet the winepreſſe of his word therein: he hath giuen it a Tower, euen a king as a ſtrong tower againſt his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, whoſe raigne the Lord con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ouer vs, if it bee his pleaſure,
<pb facs="tcp:9933:69"/> as long as the moone knoweth her courſe, &amp; the ſun his going down and let all that loue the peace of <hi>Britaine,</hi> ſay <hi>Amen.</hi> Now hee hath <hi>long expected that it ſhuld bring forth grapes, but behold it bringeth foorth wild grapes. He looked for iudgement, but behold oppreſsion, for righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but loe a crying.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe were the ſinnes of <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and you know her iudgments, he that was <hi>Ieruſalems</hi> God, is <hi>Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines</hi> God too, and therfore if ſhee paralell <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> in her iniquities, let her take heed ſhe taſt not of her plagues; God though he hath not yet begun to puniſh her in his fury yet hath he ſundry times ſhaked his rod of correction ouer her, if this will not worke amendment, her iudgement muſt be the greater.</p>
            <p>Fearefull was the caſe of <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria,</hi> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Gods puniſhments could not moue to repentance. <hi>I haue
<pb facs="tcp:9933:69"/> giuen you cleanneſſe of teeth in al your Cities,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 4.</note> 
               <hi>and ſcarceneſſe of Bread in all your places, yet haue yee not returned vnto me ſaith the Lord God. I haue with holden the raine from you when there was yet three moneths to the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt, and I cauſed it to ruine vpon one Citie, and brought a drought vpon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, yet haue yee not returned vnto me ſaith the Lord. Pestilence haue I ſent amongſt you after the manner of Egipt, and yet ye haue not returned vnto me ſaith the Lord. I haue ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten you with, blaſting and mildew, &amp;c. yet ye haue not returned vnto me ſaith the Lord God.</hi> The Lord hath not hitherto dealt with vs after our ſinnes, nor plagued vs according to the multitude of our iniquities, yet he hath made it manifeſt that he is diſpleaſed with vs: His mercy hath pulled backe his hand from draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſword of vengeance againſt vs, yet hee hath left vs ſundry to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens
<pb facs="tcp:9933:70"/> that hee is angred with our ſinnes. It is not long ſince that the <hi>heauens were made as braſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 28.23.</note> 
               <hi>and the Earth as yron,</hi> nay, the very waters became as yron or as braſſe ſo that neither the heauens from aboue, nor the earth, or water from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low did aford comforts for the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of man.</p>
            <p>This extraordinary cold diſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rature of the ayre might by an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiperiſtaſis</hi> haue kindled ſome heate of zeale &amp; deuotion in our breſts; when it had not the expected ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,<note place="margin">Pſal. 105.16</note> then he <hi>Called for a dearth vpon the land, and deſtroied our prouiſion of bread:</hi> euen ſuch a famine, that if we were not releeued from forraine countries, <hi>Ten women might bake their bread in one Ouen,</hi> as the Lord ſpeaketh, Leuit. 26.26.</p>
            <p>But all this hath not brought vs vpon our knees, nor humbled our ſoules before our God, therefore
<pb facs="tcp:9933:70"/> once againe, he hath put life in his meſſenger of death, and ſet him on foote, which heretofore of late yeres hath raged in this city, like a man of warre, and like a gyant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhed with wine, and beſtirred himſelfe (though not with the like violence) almoſt in euery part of this kingdome:<note place="margin">Pſal. 91.6.</note> I meane the <hi>peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence that walketh in the darkeneſſe, and the ſickneſſe that hath killed many thouſands at noone day:</hi> all theſe are infallible tokens that he is offended with our ſinnes: Howbeit he is ſo mercifull that he will not ſuffer his whole diſpleaſure as yet to ariſe,
<q>
                  <l>— Horum ſi ſingula duras</l>
                  <l>Flectere non poſſunt, poterint tame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omnia, mentes.</l>
               </q> If each of theſe by themſelues can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not preuaile with vs, yet if they be all put together, they may ſerue (as a threefold cord) to draw vs vnto repentance. If theſe be not of force but ſtill wee continue to blow vp
<pb facs="tcp:9933:71"/> the coales of his anger, then let vs know for a certainty, that they are the forewarners of a greater euill, as the cracking of the houſe is a forewarning of his fall: theſe bee but the flaſhing lightnings, the thunderbolt will come after.</p>
            <p>The cloud that is long in ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering, will make the greater ſtorme: he is all this while in fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his ſtroke, that hee may giue the ſorer blow, <hi>Eurum ad ſe Zephi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vocat;</hi> hee is in bringing the windes out of his treaſures, that he may rain vpon our heads a ſhowre of vengeance which ſhall bee the portion of al the vngodly to drink.</p>
            <p>I beganne like a <hi>Barrabas,</hi> I will not end like <hi>Boanarges:</hi> my ſong had an <hi>Exordium</hi> of mercy, I am loath to bring for an <hi>Epilogue</hi> a thunderclap of iudgment. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (my beloued Brethren) now that you ſee the true cauſes of the
<pb facs="tcp:9933:71"/> ruines of euery common-wealth and the iudgement that hangeth ouer your heads (like <hi>Damocles</hi> his ſword) for our iniquities; flatter your ſelues no longer in your own ſinnes, but turne vnto him by ſpee<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy and vnfained repentance, that hee may repent him of the euill, &amp; turne away his plagues from you: let the wanton leaue his dallying, and the drunkard his carrowſing, and the Vſurer his biting, and the ſwearer his blaſpheming, and the oppreſſor his grinding, and euery one amend one in time, before the Lords wrath bee further kindled: then will the Lord bee mercifull vnto this land: hee will quicklie turne the ſowre lookes of an angry and ſinne reuenging Iudge, into the ſmiling countenance of a mild and gentle Father. Hee will take the rodde which he hath prepared for you, and burne it in the fire.
<pb facs="tcp:9933:72"/> Theſe plagues which doe hang o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you for your iniquities, he will blow away with the breath of his noſtrils, as hee did the Egyptian Graſhoppers into the red ſea: he will command his deſtroying An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell to put vp his ſword into the ſheath, he will open the windowes of heauen, and power downe a bleſſing vpon you without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>Then ſhall you be bleſſed in the Citie and bleſſed in the field, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at your going out, and bleſſed at your comming in, and whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you put your hands vnto ſhall be bleſſed; your ſonnes ſhall<note n="a" place="margin">Pſa. 129.4.</note> 
               <hi>grow vp as Oliue branches, and your daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſhall be as the</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 144.</note> 
               <hi>poliſhed corners of the Temple.</hi> Your grounds ſhall ſo abound with grane that the tillers ſhall laugh and ſing; your garners ſhall be full and plenteous with all manner of ſtore<note n="c" place="margin">Ioel. 2.24.</note> 
               <hi>your preſses ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:9933:72"/> abound with Oyle and wine, your ſheepe ſhall bring forth thouſands, and tenne thouſands in your fields;</hi> Euery thing ſhall proſper, nothing ſhall ſtoppe the current of Gods bleſſings, <hi>there ſhall be no decay, nor leading into cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity, and no complayning in your ſtreetes;</hi> and which is better then all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heſe, hee will giue you faithfull &amp; painefull Paſtors to feede you, his ſpirite to comfort you, his word to inſtruct you, his wiſedome to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect you, his Angels to watch ouer you, his grace to aſſiſt you, and in a word, <hi>He will be your God, and you ſhall be his people:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſther. 6.9</note> 
               <hi>thus ſhall it be done vnto all thoſe whome the King of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſhall honour:</hi> ſo that all the world ſhal wonder at your felicity, &amp; ſay, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord which taketh plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the proſperity of his ſeruants, &amp; happy are the people that bee in ſuch a caſe, yea bleſſed are al they which haue the Lord for their God;</hi> thus wil he be
<pb facs="tcp:9933:73"/> with you, and direct you in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert of this world, till he bring you into a faire and Goodly place, the promiſed land, a land that floweth with better things then abou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance of Milke and Honey, the celeſtiall Paradiſe, the heauenly Canaan, the kingdome of glory prepared for you from the beginning of the world, euen that kingdome where the King is verity, the Lawes chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the Angels your company, the Peace felicitie, the life eternity. To this kingdom, the God of al mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy bring vs for his ſake that bought vs with his owne blood, to whom with the Father and the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, three perſons in trinitie, and one God in vnitie, be aſcribed all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor &amp; glory, power and Maieſtie, both now and for euermore A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:9933:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
